<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Quakers folly made manifest to all men: or a true relation of what passed in three disputations at Sandwich, April, 12, 13, 19, 1659. between three Quakers, and a minister, viz. Mr. Samuel Fisher, George Whithead, Richard Hubberthorn, and Thomas Danson wherein many popish tenents were by them maintained, and by him refuted. Occasioned by an imperfect and (in many things) false relation of the said disputations, published by R. Hubberthorn, one of the three Quakers, which said relation is also censur'd and amended. Together with a brief narrative of some remarkable passages. / By Tho. Danson, late fellow of Magd. Coll. Oxon, and now minister of the Gospel at Sandwich in Kent.</title>
            <author>Danson, Thomas, d. 1694.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 131 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81734</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D215</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E2255_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34492</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872378</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872378</idno>
            <idno type="VID">124811</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81734)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 124811)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 244:E2255[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Quakers folly made manifest to all men: or a true relation of what passed in three disputations at Sandwich, April, 12, 13, 19, 1659. between three Quakers, and a minister, viz. Mr. Samuel Fisher, George Whithead, Richard Hubberthorn, and Thomas Danson wherein many popish tenents were by them maintained, and by him refuted. Occasioned by an imperfect and (in many things) false relation of the said disputations, published by R. Hubberthorn, one of the three Quakers, which said relation is also censur'd and amended. Together with a brief narrative of some remarkable passages. / By Tho. Danson, late fellow of Magd. Coll. Oxon, and now minister of the Gospel at Sandwich in Kent.</title>
                  <author>Danson, Thomas, d. 1694.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[8], 60, [4] p., plate   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.H. for John Allen at the Rising Sun in Pauls Church-Yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With a preliminary imprimatur leaf and two final advertisement leaves.</note>
                  <note>The plate bears the sign and address of the publisher.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July:".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hubberthorn, Richard, 1628-1662 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Fisher, Samuel, 1605-1665 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Whitehead, George, 1636?-1723 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:124811:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Quakers Folly Made manifeſt to all men: Or a True RELATION of what paſſed in Three DISPUTATIONS at <hi>Sandwich, April,</hi> 12, 13, 19, 1659. between three Quakers, and a Miniſter, <hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>Samuel Fiſher, George Whithead, Richard Hubberthorn,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Danſon.</hi> Wherein many Popiſh Tenents were by them Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, and by him Refuted. OCCASIONED By an imperfect and (in many things) falſe Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſaid Diſputations, Publiſhed by <hi>R. Hub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berthorn,</hi> one of the Three Quakers, which ſaid Relation is alſo Cenſur'd and amended. Together with a brief Narrative of ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Paſſages.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Tho. Danſon,</hi> late Fellow of <hi>Magd.</hi> Coll. <hi>Oxon,</hi> and now Miniſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Sandwich</hi> in <hi>Kent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Second Edition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. H.</hi> for <hi>John Allen</hi> at the Riſing Sun in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-Yard, 1659.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:124811:2"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Joſeph Caryl.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>June 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>, 1659.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:124811:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:124811:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:124811:3"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE TO the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Erhaps thou wilt wonder, that I ſhould meddle with ſuch a Generation, as the Quakers, and thou maiſt be apt to think, that my time hangs on the Lug (as we ſay) and will not off at any conſiderable
<pb facs="tcp:124811:4"/> rate: But that thy wonder may ceaſe, and thy miſtake be rectified, I refer thee to the Narrative hereto annexed; which I hope will give thee ſatisfaction: The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of my appearance in Print, the Title Page does truly inform thee of. I can aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure thee, it never was my ambition to appear ſo publickly, and had I conſidered the likelihood of the Quakers Printing, which would neceſſitate mine, I think I ſhould have waved any diſcourſe with them. But repentance is now too late, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps unmeet, for God can ſerve himſelf by the meaneſt Inſtruments, among which I willingly rank my ſelf: I verily hope thou wilt ſee the men out of their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe, and wilt find cauſe ſufficient to think and ſpeak of them with pity and compaſsion; and of their opinions, with hatred and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation. I promiſe thee Reader, no more then ſhall be performed <hi>(viz.)</hi> a true account of our diſcourſes, I mean ſo much of them as was Argumentative, and pertinent to the Queſtions under debate. For thou muſt
<pb facs="tcp:124811:4"/> know, that the Quakers, like wantons, would have their vagaries ever and anon, and then I muſt ſay ſomwhat to them, or let them have all the talk, which by the ignorance of common people, would have been a prejudice to the cauſe of God which I defended. And I therefore choſe rather to out-word them (which is the reaſon why my Anſwers are oftentimes ſo large and laxe.) Many excurſions they made into Arminian points, which I was fain to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, and to defend the Truths they oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: All which I ſhall either wholly omit, or mention very ſparingly; becauſe they are not Errours of ſo high a nature, as thoſe which are the natural Members of that deformed Monſter, we call <hi>Quakeriſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Names of Gentlemen, Miniſters, and others in the Margin, are a few (of very many) witneſses of the Terms of the Queſtions agreed to by the Quakers, and of other remarkable paſſages, and matters of fact, who will free me from the ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition of a partial Relator. <hi>That theſe
<pb facs="tcp:124811:5"/> men may proceed no further, but that their folly may be manifeſt to all men, 2</hi> Tim. <hi>3.9. And that we henceforth be no more children, toſſed to and fro with every wind of Doctrine, by the ſleight of men, and cunning craftineſſe, whereby they lie in wait to deceive, but ſpeaking the Truth in love, may grow up into him in all things, which is the Head, even Chriſt,</hi> is the earneſt Prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy Servant for Jeſus ſake, <hi>Tho. Danſon.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Sandwich,</hi>
                  <date>May <hi>24, 1659.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:124811:5"/>
            <head>An ACCOUNT of a DISPUTE <hi>April</hi> 12th between three QUAKERS, M. <hi>S. Fiſher, G. Whithead, R. Hubberthorn,</hi> and <hi>Tho. Danſon.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter a brief account of the occaſion of our meeting, and a ſhort prayer for a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing upon it, we began with this Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, <hi>Whether every man that cometh into the world be enlightened by Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>R. Hubberth.</speaker>
               <p>I bear witneſs to the Truth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. Danſon.</speaker>
               <p>But what light is it you intend? we grant that every man hath ſome light, by which he diſcerns (though dimly) many ſins, and duties, and ſeveral Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine attributes, but <hi>the myſtery of godlineſſe,</hi> as it is ſumm'd up, 1 <hi>Tim</hi> 3. <hi>ult. God manifeſt in the fleſh, juſtified in the ſpirit,</hi> &amp;c. we deny that all men have the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>R Hubberthorn.</speaker>
               <p>The light is but one, and that I teſtifie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. Danſon.</speaker>
               <p>The lights mentioned, <hi>viz.</hi> natural and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernatural light, are two, and though all have the one, yet but few have the other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:124811:6"/>
               <speaker>R. Hubberthorn.</speaker>
               <p>Thou ſpeakeſt out of thy dark mind, becauſe the true light hath not come over and comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. Danſon.</speaker>
               <p>Your judgement of me I value not, but pray forbear your cenſures, and let us ſpeak to the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. If your meaning be that the knowledge of the Goſpel is vouchſafed by Chriſt to every man, I ſhall ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther expect your proof, or ſhall prove the contrary my ſelf.
<stage>Here the man was ſilent.</stage>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. Danſon.</speaker>
               <p>I take your ſilence for conſent to my offer of proving againſt your Doctrine. And thus I prove it falſe, <hi>Pſal</hi> 147.19, 20. <hi>He ſheweth his Word unto Jacob, his statutes and his judgements unto Iſrael: He hath not dealt ſo with any Nation, and as for his judgements they have not known them.</hi> 'Tis plain from Scripture that by the Word and Statutes and Judgments, are meant the ſupernatural light or knowledge of the Goſpel. And the Pſalmiſt does aſſert that no Nation beſides the Jews had this knowledge at that time; which overthrows your aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion, for you ſpeak of a light which every man hath in all ages and generations. And I ſhall add another plain Scripture, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.12. where ſpeaking of the ſtate of the whole body of the Gentiles before Chriſts coming in the fleſh, he ſaies, they were <hi>without Chriſt, ſtrangers from the Covenant of promiſe, having no hope, and without God in the world.</hi> Obſerve, they who had no hope, that is, no ground o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hope of ſalvation, were ignorant of the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes the g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ound of hope, and ſo of God in Chriſt the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of hope, and ſo of the ſumme of the Goſpel, or light of Chriſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. Whithead.</speaker>
               <p>Thou bringeſt a place out of <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.12. to pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve that Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt enlightens not every man that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth into the world, and thou haſt given us thy meaning co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>trary to the Scripture, which ſaies the Gentiles have <hi>the Law in their hearts,</hi> Rom. 2.15.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:124811:6"/>
               <speaker>T. Danſon.</speaker>
               <p>You prove not my interpretation of either of the Scriptures I urged unſound, but bringeſt me ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Scripture, and I muſt let you go your own way. As for that Scripture, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.15. 'tis ſpoken of the natural light, for 'tis oppoſed to the knowledge of the Jews. And the words are not the <hi>law,</hi> but the <hi>work</hi> or effects of <hi>the law written in their hearts,</hi> ſuch as <hi>accuſing</hi> and <hi>excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> mentioned in the latter end of the verſe; and there is a great deal of difference between the <hi>law</hi> and <hi>the work of it,</hi> though you do not (it ſeems) underſtand it. And it is beſides my buſineſſe to inform you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. Whithead.</speaker>
               <p>Thou ſayeſt 'tis meant of a natural light, whereas 'tis ſaid to be the <hi>knowledge</hi> of whatſoever <hi>might be known of God,</hi> Rom. 1.19.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. Danſon.</speaker>
               <p>The Apoſtle intends that what might be known of God, without the preaching of the Goſpel, was known to the Gentiles, <hi>v.</hi> 16, 17. 'tis by the <hi>Gospel</hi> that <hi>the righteouſneſſe of God is revealed,</hi> and <hi>John</hi> 4.22. Chriſt tels the <hi>Samar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tan</hi> woman, that the Jews (exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively) <hi>knew what they worſhipped,</hi> and that <hi>ſalvation was of the Jews.</hi> And in reſpect of this knowledge re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed by the Goſpel, the Scripture ſaies that the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles <hi>have their understandings darkned,</hi> Eph. 4.18.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. Whithead.</speaker>
               <p>That place ſaies that the Gentiles were not ſo enlightened as afterwards: For 'tis ſaid that <hi>Chriſt was given for a light to the Gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iles.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. Danſon.</speaker>
               <p>You give your meaning of the Scripture which you will not allow us to do. But as for that Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture which is <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.6. it proves not that Chriſt was a light to the Gentiles in every age and generation, but the contrary, in that Chriſt was not to be a light to them till his coming in the fleſh, and it was fulfilled, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.46, 47. <hi>Lo, we turn to the Gentiles. For ſo hath the Lord commanded us ſaying, I have ſet thee to be a light of the Gentiles.</hi> As for the place in the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> it denies that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:124811:7"/> the Gentiles had been at all enlightened by Chriſt (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe you mean as God) <hi>ch.</hi> 2.13. The Apoſtle ſaies in that eſtate before Chriſts coming, they were afarre off, <hi>viz.</hi> from God and Chriſt ſpoken of, <hi>v.</hi> 12. and the knowledge of them. And <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.18. he ſaies that they <hi>were alienated from the life of God,</hi> which imports that their underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings were no more capable of the knowledge of God, then creatures of one kind of life to converſe with thoſe of another. Gods underſtanding is his life, as he is a reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able being, and theſe Gentiles wanted what ſome have by eſpecial gift, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.20. <hi>an underſtanding to know him that is true;</hi> and could no more converſe with ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual objects, than bruit beaſts can with ſuch rational ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects as mans underſtanding does: So that thoſe Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures put together do aſſert that the body of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, for ages and Generations wanted the light of the Goſpel, and light in their underſtandings, the difference of which you may conceive by the light of the Sun which is external light (and ſo the Goſpel) and the light in the eye to which anſwers an underſtanding to know him that is true, and both of them are neceſſary, or elſe a blind man might ſee when there is light, and the ſeeing man when there is none.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. Whithead.</speaker>
               <p>Thou makeſt the Goſpel to be an outward light (in the darkneſſe of thy own reaſoning) but the Scripture ſaies 'tis an inward light, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4 6. the Apoſtle ſaies it <hi>ſhines out of darkneſſe in their hearts.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. Danſon.</speaker>
               <p>You ſhew much ignorance in your interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. The Apoſtle ſpeaks of material light, and argues from the effect of one creating word to another, that by the like word of command he had the light or knowledge of Chriſt in his underſtanding, which was given not for his own uſe only, but to be communicated to others. As for the phraſe <hi>in their hearts,</hi> it imports but the ſame thing with that expreſſion, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.18. <hi>The eyes of your
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:124811:7"/> underſtanding being enlightened.</hi> The light by which the Goſpel is diſcerned is inward, but that makes not againſt the Goſpels being an outward light. But what's this to the enlightning of every man by Chriſt? Reply to the Scriptures brought againſt that aſſertion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. Whithead.</speaker>
               <p>The Apoſtle ſaies the light of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the glory of God in the face of Chriſt ſhined in their hearts, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. Danſon.</speaker>
               <p>In whoſe hearts? nor of all mankind, but of the Apoſtles, and ſome others, a ſmall number in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of the reſt who were not enlightned; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtle ſaies, that <hi>the Goſpel was hid to them that are loſt,</hi> v. 3. and that there are ſome, <hi>to whom the light of the Goſpel doth not ſhine,</hi> v. 4. And 'tis elſewhere ſpoken of as a diſtinguiſhing mercy to know the myſteries of the Kingdom of Heaven, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.11. It was given to the Diſciples, not to others. And to the ſame effect, <hi>Luke</hi> 10.21. Chriſt gives thanks to his Father, that whilſt he hid the ſecrets of the Goſpel from Scribes and Phariſees, he revealed them to others.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. Whithead.</speaker>
               <p>The Scripture ſaies that the Kingdom of God was in the Phariſees, <hi>Luke</hi> 17.21. and therfore it denies not but that they did know the myſteries of the Kingdom.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. Danſon.</speaker>
               <p>That expreſſion may import that the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom which they did upon miſtake look for without them, was indeed a Kingdom within them. [To which I ſhall adde, that upon ſecond thoughts, I judge the moſt ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine interpretation to be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>among you</hi> (ſo the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſ. may be rendred) <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.43. meaning of the preaching of the Goſpel by Chriſt in perſon and his Diſciples, and this threat of taking away the Kingdom of God from them, is directed againſt the Phariſees, <hi>v.</hi> 45. <hi>The Phariſees perceived that he ſpake of them.]</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>R. Hubberthorn.</speaker>
               <p>The form of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ound words is, that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:124811:8"/> Chriſt enlightens every man that cometh into the world, <hi>John</hi> 1.9.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. Danſon.</speaker>
               <p>The mean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng of thoſe words cannot be as the letter of them does import, for then the Scripture would contradict it ſelf; but it muſt be either that Chriſt inl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ghtens every man that is inl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ghtened, or elſe that he inlightens ſome of every Nation, kindred, tongue and people, as the phraſe is, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.9.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>R. Hubberthorn.</speaker>
               <p>The Scripture ſaies <hi>every man,</hi> and thou ſaieſt but ſome, who ſhall be believed, thou or the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle? Thou makeſt <hi>John</hi> a liar.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. Danſon.</speaker>
               <p>No ſuch matter, I make not the Apoſtle a liar. For the indefinite phraſe hath a reſtrained ſenſe, as elſewhere in the Scripture, Chriſt <hi>taſted death for every m n,</hi> Heb. 2.9. when as he died but for a certain number, as appears by that very place, <hi>v.</hi> 10. <hi>In bringing many ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s to glory.</hi> Thoſe whom Chriſt brings to glory are thoſe for whom he taſted death, but the former are but <hi>many ſons,</hi> and therefore not the latter: the every man for whom he died muſt be limited by the many ſons whom he brings to glory.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>R. Hubberthorn.</speaker>
               <p>Then it ſeems thou denieſt that Chriſt died for all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. Danſon.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, that I do, and 'tis more than you can prove.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. Whithead.</speaker>
               <p>I witneſſe according to the Scripture, that Chriſt died for all, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14. <hi>If one died for all, then were all dead.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. Danſon.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis ſpoken of thoſe who were converts and believers, whoſe ſanctification was the end of Chriſt's death, and for whom Chriſt roſe, and who therefore did ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e with him. As for the meaning of the words 'tis this, that the neceſſity of Chriſt's dying imported the miſery of their condition, in that they were dead ſpiritually, and obnoxious to eternal death, and the love of Chriſt which
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:124811:8"/> made him come in at a pinch, to help when none elſe could, is a great conſtraint to obedience upon all the dead for whom Chriſt died. That place is fully parallel and opens this (putting but Chriſt in ſtead of God into the former clauſe) <hi>God commendeth his love toward us</hi> (ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of believers, <hi>v.</hi> 1, 2.) <hi>in that while we were yet ſinners, Chriſt died for us,</hi> Rom. 5.8.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. Whithead.</speaker>
               <p>Still thou perverteſt Scripture by thy meanings.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. Danſon.</speaker>
               <p>I pervert it not, but I reconcile the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture to it ſelf.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. Whithead.</speaker>
               <p>The Scripture is at unity with it ſelf, and needs not thy reconciling. 'Tis ſaid, <hi>the Scripture can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be broken.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. Danſon.</speaker>
               <p>I ſay ſo too, that the Scripture is at unity with it ſelf, but withall that it ſeems to diſagree, and cannot approve it ſelf to our underſtandings, without the mediation of a meaning or interpretation. It was an u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual thing with Chriſt to ſpeak words of a doubtful ſenſe, as <hi>John</hi> 3.19. <hi>Destroy this Temple,</hi> which they underſtood of the material Temple (he being in it at the time, <hi>v.</hi> 15. and likely enough ſpeaking with his eye as well as his tongue) <hi>v.</hi> 20. but he meant of <hi>the temple of his body,</hi> v. 21.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. Whithead.</speaker>
               <p>Thou art ſuch a giver of meanings as they were, who gave it contrary to Chriſts meaning</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. Danſon.</speaker>
               <p>Whether I be ſuch a one or no is not for you to judge in your own cauſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> leave it to the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding hearers. But in the mean while the place ſerves my purpoſe, <hi>viz.</hi> to prove that Chriſt's meaning may be miſtaken, when his words are taken in the moſt ordinary and literal ſenſe, and ſo it would be, if by <hi>every man,</hi> we ſhould underſtand every individual man; ſo that 'tis your ſelf, and not I that am ſuch a giver of meanings as the Jews.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. Whithead.</speaker>
               <p>How canſt thou prove that thou art to give meanings to Scripture?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:124811:9"/>
               <speaker>T. Danſon.</speaker>
               <p>I do not pretend to power to give mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to Scripture (as your phraſe is) if you mean there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, adding any thing to the Scripture which is not in it, but to find out what already is, by cauſing the Scriptures with the Cherubims to face one another; that is my du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and all other mens. This the Scripture warrants, Neh. 8.8. <hi>So they read in the Book, in the Law of God di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly, and gave the ſenſe, and cauſed them to underſtand the reading.</hi> And I ſhould be glad to know of any of you who are againſt meanings, how you can underſtand ſuch Scriptures as theſe without a meaning, <hi>God is not a man that he ſhould repent. It repenteth me that I have made man. God tempted Abraham. God tempts no man. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer not a fool according to his folly. Anſwer a fool accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his folly.</hi> And once more, <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>James<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> The former ſaies, <hi>that a man is juſtified by Faith without the works of the Law, Rom.</hi> 3.28. And the other flatly contradicts him in terms, that <hi>by works a man is justified, and not by Faith only, Jam.</hi> 2.24. When as any of theſe do ſweetly conſent, if the ambiguity of phraſes be once removed: As for inſtance in <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>James,</hi> the one ſpeaks of being formally juſtified, the other declarative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Juſtification in <hi>Paul</hi> is oppoſite to the condemnation of a ſinner in general, and juſtification in <hi>James</hi> is oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to the condemnation of an hypocrite in particular. In <hi>Pauls</hi> ſenſe a ſinner is abſolved, in <hi>James</hi>'s ſenſe a believer is approved. [So <hi>Diodat</hi> whoſe words I uſed, but forgot to name him in the diſcourſe] Here the two diſputants had nothing to ſay, but what was abſurd and impertinent; and thereupon I deſired we might leave what had been ſpoken to the hearers judgment, and to go on to another Queſtion, which at length was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed to.</p>
               <p>The Second Queſtion was, <hi>Whether in this life the Saints attain to a ſtate of perfection or freedom from ſin?</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:124811:9"/> This they held in the affirmative.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. Danſon.</speaker>
               <p>Your Doctrine of perfection is againſt the tenour of the Scripture, let us hear what you can ſay for the proof of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>R. Hubberthorn.</speaker>
               <p>1 John 3.9. <hi>Whoſoever is born of God doth not commit ſin.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. Danſon.</speaker>
               <p>That cannot be meant of freedom from ſin; but either there is an emphaſis in the word ſin, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending under that general term one kind or ſort of ſin, which is ſpoken of, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.16. <hi>There is a ſin unto death.</hi> Or if not on the Subſtantive, on the Verb <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> which notes to make a trade or buſineſſe of ſin, as 'tis explain'd, <hi>v.</hi> 8. where he uſes the ſame verb, <hi>for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil ſinneth from the beginning.</hi> He hath never ceaſed to ſinne ſince he began, thus indeed the Saints ſin not, but a courſe of ſin is broken of<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and there is not ſuch a free trade between the ſoul and ſin, as in the ſtate of unrege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neracy, whereof this is given for one character, <hi>that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ceaſe to ſin,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.14.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. Whithead.</speaker>
               <p>Thou wreſteſt the Scriptures to thy own deſtruction.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. Danſon.</speaker>
               <p>No, I wreſt them not, if I do, ſhew wherein. And if you will obſerve, either it muſt be meant of all Saints or none, for the New birth agrees to all, if then the phraſe excludes the being of ſin in ſome, it muſt in all; and mark the reaſon given, <hi>becauſe his ſeed remaineth in him, and he cannot ſin, becauſe he is born of God:</hi> Now the ſeed remains in all, as well as any; now leſt you ſhould be ſo mad as to aſſert all Saints to be free from ſin, pray read 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.8. <hi>If we ſay that we have no ſin, we deceive our ſelves,</hi> and this is ſpoken of ſuch perſons, as of whom it is denied that they commit ſin, perſons that had <hi>fellowſhip with the Father and his Son Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> v. 3.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. <hi>Fiſher.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>Pray do not multiply words to no purpoſe,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:124811:10"/> but read, <hi>v. ult. If we ſay that we have not ſinned, we make him a liar.</hi> The born of God ſhould lie if they did deny themſelves to have ſinned, before they were in the new birth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. Danſon.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, you muſt not think to put us off ſo, <hi>v.</hi> 8. 'tis <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and the other is, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Suppoſe the latter verſe were to be underſtood of the ſin, which preceded the new birth, yet the former is expreſly <hi>de praeſenti,</hi> that <hi>we have</hi> (not have had) <hi>no ſin;</hi> and yet I ſee nothing to the contrary, but <hi>that we hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> not ſinned, v. ult.</hi> may relate to particular acts of ſin in the ſtate of the new birth, denied either in whole or in part.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. Whithead.</speaker>
               <p>Phil. 3.15. <hi>As many as he perfect let us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e thus minded.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. Danſon.</speaker>
               <p>For the phraſe upon which you ground your notion, 'tis uſed in a comparative ſenſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.6. ſpeaks of grown Chriſtians, who could fancy the Goſpel in a plain dreſs, whom he cals perfect in compariſon of others, as he cals <hi>Babes in Chriſt, carnal</hi> in reſpect of thoſe who are more ſpiritual, <hi>Ch.</hi> 3.1. And often in Scripture perfect is put for upright, and made ſynony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, or of the ſame import, <hi>Job</hi> 1.1. that man (mean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng <hi>Job</hi>) was perfect and upright; that perfect is not meant in your ſenſe, appears by <hi>c.</hi> 9.20. <hi>If I ſay I am pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> (his mouth) <hi>ſhall alſo prove me perverſe.</hi> Sinceri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y <hi>Job</hi> all along avouched, but perfection ſuch as he m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ght j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtifie h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mſelf by, he denies. But to return to the place, <hi>Phi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 3.12. He denies that he was yet per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, whilſt in a breath he affirms himſelf ſo. The per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection he denies, is the reſurrection of the dead, <hi>v.</hi> 11. that is by an uſual Metonymy of the ſubject for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nct, that meaſure of holineſſe which accompanies tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtate, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch we ſhall find to be excluſive of ſin, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.2. <hi>We ſhall be lik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> him, meaning Chriſt, when he appears.</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:124811:10"/> But how ſhall Chriſt appear, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. <hi>ult. appear the ſecond time without ſin.</hi> Put it together, and the perfection <hi>Paul</hi> denies, is the ſtate of the reſurrection, which is to be without ſin. The perfection he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffirms, is comparative, in reſpect of Chriſtians of lower attainments, who could not aſſent to all the Doctrines of the Goſpel, <hi>v.</hi> 15. <hi>If in any thing ye (i. e.</hi> ſome of you) <hi>be otherwiſe minded.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. <hi>Fiſher.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>I will prove from the Scripture ſuch a ſtate of perfection, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. <hi>Bleſſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re the undefiled in the way,</hi> v. 1. <hi>They alſo do no iniquity,</hi> v. 2. Do you mark eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry word?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. Danſon.</speaker>
               <p>Yes Sir, we mark the words, but I might expect a reply to what I have urged againſt the Scriptures brought by your friend. As for the phraſes, they are hyperbolical, <hi>v.</hi> 6. <hi>Then I ſhall not be aſhamed when I have respect to all thy Commandm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s,</hi> in reſpect of deſign and endeavour, though falling ſhort in accompliſhment, that <hi>v.</hi> explains the other two you brought. [I ſhall add, that <hi>David</hi> excludes himſelf out of a bleſſed ſtate, if un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled, and doing no iniquity be meant ſtrictly. His wiſh, <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. and other paſſages <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the Pſalms, ſhew, that he was not free from ſinne, which ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <hi>David</hi> did not intend; for <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32 2. he pronounces the man bleſſed which hath <hi>no guilt in his ſpirit,</hi> or ſincere, which himſelf was at that time, though under th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> guilt of a great ſinne, <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. which is by interpreters ſuppoſed to be the ſame ſins, for which <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. was compoſed.] But Mr. <hi>Fiſher</hi> can you produce one ſingle example of a perfect Saint in your ſenſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. <hi>Fiſher.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>Yes <hi>(Thomas Danſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n)</hi> that I can. 'Tis in <hi>Luke</hi> 1.6. <hi>And they (Zachary</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth) were bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h righteous before God</hi> (not before man only, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re God) <hi>walk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng in all the Commandments</hi> (nor in ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me few o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> many, but all) <hi>and O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dinances of the Lord blameleſs.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:124811:11"/>
               <speaker>T. Danſon.</speaker>
               <p>Methinks Sir, you bring in this Scripture with pomp and ceremony, yet it will not do: For firſt, how doth it appear that righteous before God, is meant a perfect inherent righteouſneſſe? ſeeing a believers per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon with his works are accepted with God, though his works be not perfect, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.4. <hi>By Faith Abel offered to God a more excellent Sacrifice than Cain, by which he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained witneſs that he was righteous,</hi> &amp;c. And ſecondly, how do you prove blameleſſe to be meant otherwiſe than comparatively, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.15. <hi>Blameleſs, without rebuke in the midst of a crooked and perverſe Nation, among whom ye ſhine as lights in the world.</hi> In the ſame ſenſe may <hi>Luke</hi> underſtand the phraſe. And if you mark, the very ſame phraſe is uſed of <hi>Pauls</hi> external conformity to the Law; when he was ſo far from perfect, that he had no Grace at all, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Touching the righteouſneſſe which is in the Law blameleſſe.</hi> v. 5. <hi>Touching the Law a Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſce.</hi> Now how they were blameleſſe, you find by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, <hi>Luke</hi> 18.10, 11. <hi>Not as other men are, I faſt twice in the week,</hi> &amp;c. I bring this inſtance to let you know that the phraſe ſimply conſidered, will be ſo far from importing perfection of Grace, that it will not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port any Grace. But in a word, to put it out of doubt, <hi>Zacharias</hi> of whom theſe words are uſed, whence you ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther him to be free from ſin, is found guilty at the very time that this deſcription agreed to him, of unbelief, and was with dumbneſſe puniſhed for it, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.10. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold thou ſhalt be dumb, and not able to speak, until the day that theſe things be performed, becauſe thou believeſt not my words,</hi> &amp;c. 'Tis the meſſage of <hi>Gabriel</hi> the Angel to <hi>Za<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>harias, v.</hi> 19. You ſee Mr. <hi>Fiſher,</hi> your pomp in the bringing in of this Scripture was meer waſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. <hi>Fiſher.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>But <hi>Tho. Danſon,</hi> there is no ſuch thing m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntioned of <hi>Elizab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th,</hi> and if there be one inſtance, it ſufficeth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:124811:11"/>
               <speaker>T. Danſon.</speaker>
               <p>But Sir, your Argument is drawn from the import of the phraſes, and if the phraſes are applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to him though guilty of actual ſin, then they will not argue her to be more free from ſin than him, though there be no mention of any of her ſins.—Pray Sir, ſeeing you have nothing to reply, but God has ſtopped your mouth, let me hear what anſwer you can give to that Scripture which hath run much in my mind a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this Doctrine, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.20. <hi>There is not a juſt man upon earth that doth good and ſinneth not.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>R. Hubberthorn.</speaker>
               <p>It cannot be meant as thou wouldſt have it, for the man Chriſt then were not a juſt man, which I think thou wilt not ſay.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. Danſon.</speaker>
               <p>I deſir'd Mr. <hi>Fiſhers</hi> anſwer, and not yours. But ſeeing he is ſilenced, I will anſwer you: What a wretch are you to make ſuch an Inference? was not Chriſt God as well as man? And could a nature tainted with ſin be taken into a perſonal union with the Divine Nature? The place I urge excludes any meer man from perfection in this life.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. <hi>Fiſher.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>I will give thee an anſwer <hi>Tho. Danſon,</hi> We grant the truth in that Scripture, the juſt man there ſpoken of, is not on earth, for he is redeemed from the earth, and in the Revelation he is ſaid to be a dweller in Heaven, whereas the wrath of God is ſaid to come upon the Inhabitants of the earth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. Danſon.</speaker>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Fiſher</hi> you run very low at laſt, this is a meer evaſion, I verily believe in your own judgment and intention, becauſe you think you muſt ſay ſomwhat. Can you poſſibly think that the j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt mans being in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in reſpect of his diſpoſition and affection, and in his Head Chriſt, excludes his local abode on earth? We ſay indeed that no ſuch juſt man as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks of, is to be found on earth, but in Heaven, which is a place of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode, as well as a ſtate of bliſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:124811:12"/>
               <speaker>R. Hubberthorn.</speaker>
               <p>In <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.23. <hi>Spirits of juſt men made perfect;</hi> this is ſpoken of them to whom the Apoſtle writes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. Danſon.</speaker>
               <p>The pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce doth not import the perfection of any men on earth, but ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aking of the ſtate we are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced to under the Goſpel by Chriſt, he ſaies we are one body with them in Heaven, and have the ſame title with them in poſſeſſion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>R. Hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>berthorn.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>Thus with thy meanings thou per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verteſt Scripture.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. Danſon.</speaker>
               <p>I leave it to the judgement of judicious hearers, whether I have perverted Scripture or no, and ſo pray do you.</p>
               <p>The third Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtion debated on was (though with much ado) at length ſtated in theſe terms; <hi>Whether our good works are the meritorious cauſe of our juſtification?</hi> And <hi>Mr. Fiſher</hi> held it in the Affirmative.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. Fiſher.</speaker>
               <p>Thus I prove that our good works are the meritorious cauſe of our juſtification, by a rule that you own, <hi>Contraria contrariorum ratio,</hi> whence I argue thus; If our evil works are the meritorious cauſe of our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, then out good works are the meritorious cauſe of our <hi>non</hi>-condemnation or juſtification; But our evil works are the meritorious cauſe of our condemnation, therefore our good works are the meritorious cauſe of our <hi>non</hi>-condemnation or juſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fication.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. Danſon.</speaker>
               <p>Now you ſhew your ſelf a rank Papiſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed. We deny your conſequence, becauſe our evil works are perfectly evil, but our good works are but imperfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly good, and any one evil is a violation of the Law, and deſerves the penalty of the Law, but any one or more, good work is not the fulfillin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the Law. [Let me add, that there is no conſequence in that Popiſh Argument, notwithſtand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng that Canon, becauſe our good and evil works are not abſolute contraries, the one being perfectly
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:124811:12"/> evil, the other but imperfectly good, <hi>Mulum oritur ex quolibet defectu, Bonum fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ex integris cauſis,</hi> which latter appears by <hi>Iſa.</hi> 64.6. <hi>All our righteouſneſses</hi> (not our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſes only) <hi>are as filthy rags.</hi> And again, thus the rule will allow to argue; Evil works which are the violation, of the Law deſerve damnation; <hi>Ergo,</hi> good works which are the fulfilling of the Law deſerve ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And we know no good works ſuch, but Chriſt's. And once more in reſpect of the ſubject, the Rule will not hold, being one who owes all his good works to God, and is a finite creature, now thoſe works which merit muſt not be due, and they muſt be of infinite value, or elſe there is no proportion between them and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. And thus we might argue <hi>à contrariis.</hi> If his evil works from whom only good works are due, as from a finite creature, to an infinite Creator, do truly deſerve damnation, then his good works who owes none, and is an infinite perſon, do truly deſerve <hi>non</hi>-condemnation. But <hi>verum prius, ergo et poſterius.</hi> And to underſtand this, we muſt know that the deſert of diſobedience ariſes chiefly from the dignity of the Object againſt which ſin is committed; when as the deſert of obedience ariſes from the dignity of the ſubject by which it is performed.]</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. <hi>Fiſher.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>I will prove my conſequence from <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.18. <hi>But if ye be led of the Spirit, ye are not under the Law.</hi> Whence I argue, If they who are led by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit are not under the Law, then the leading of the Spirit is the meritorious cauſe of their not being under the Law, but they who are led by the Spirit, are not under the Law, <hi>Ergo.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. Danſon.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, you are very ſilly your ſelf, or take your hearers to be ſo, that you think this to be a proof of your former conſequence, or that there is any conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence in this Argument. You ſhould have proved that there is <hi>par ratio</hi> for the merit of good and of evil works.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:124811:13"/> And ſurely Sir, the leading of the Spirit, or Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is a fruit and effect, not a meritorious cauſe of not being under the Law, that is obliged to its penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. <hi>Fiſher.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>I will prove by another Scripture that leading by the Spirit is the meritorious cauſe of our Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11. <hi>And ſuch were ſome of you, but ye are waſhed, but ye are ſanctified, but ye are juſtified in the Name of the Lord Jeſus, and by the Spirit of our God.</hi> Obſerve, here the <hi>Co inthians</hi> are ſaid <hi>to be justified by the Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. Danſon.</speaker>
               <p>I might ſay that perhaps the clauſe ſhould be referred to Sanctification, which is in a more appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate manner attributed to the Spirits efficiency, as if the order of the words had been, <hi>but ye are ſanctified by the Spirit of our God,</hi> and ſuch tranſpoſitions are not without inſtance in the Scripture, as, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.6. <hi>Give not that which is holy to dogs, neither caſt ye your Pearls be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſwine, leſt they trample them under their feet, and turn again and rent you,</hi> where <hi>turn again and rent you,</hi> is to be joyned to <hi>the dogs,</hi> for as ſwine do trample under their feet, ſo dogs do fly upon a man, and tear him down. Or elſe <hi>juſtified by the Spirit</hi> may be meant of the Spirits application; I mean the third Perſon in the Trinity, not of the work of Grace, whereof we are the Subject</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. <hi>Fiſher.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>In the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of the <hi>Rom. v.</hi> 2. <hi>The Law of the Spirit of life in Chriſt Jeſus hath made me free from the Law of ſin and death.</hi> Now 'tis the ſame Law of the Spirit of life that is in Chriſt and the Saints.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. Danſon.</speaker>
               <p>That place is much againſt you: For the Apoſtle aſſerts the Holineſſe of mans Nature as a work of the Spirit conforming it to the Law, to be the merito<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ious cauſe of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> freedom from ſin and death; but mark withal, 'tis not that which is in us, but in Chriſt.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:124811:13"/> And though 'tis true that the ſame ſpirit is in Chriſt and the Saints, yet neither does the ſpirit in us conform us fully to the Law (notwithſtanding your vain aſſertion of perfection) nor if it did, were that conformity the merit of J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtification. [Let me add, that the Law of the Spirit of life here ſpoken of, is not only the meritorious cauſe of our freedom from death, but from the Law of ſin, or obeying of ſin as a Law; now I would fain know what precedent holineſſe in the Saints merits ſubſequent holineſſe; or whether the exerciſe of what they have, is the meritorious cauſe of what they have not, or of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, eſpecially if the <hi>law of ſin</hi> intends the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of nature, as the <hi>Law of the Spirit of life</hi> does holineſs of nature: I would be inſtructed how a nature in part corrupted can deſerve total freedom; and I am ſure the firſt work of the Spirit renews our natures but in part.]</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. <hi>Fiſher.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>Pray read on, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.4. <hi>That the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of the Law might be fulfilled in us, who walk not after the fleſh, but after the Spirit.</hi> This place ſaies the righteouſneſſe of the Law is fulfilled in the perſons of the Saints.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. Danſon.</speaker>
               <p>Sure Sir, you never read <hi>v.</hi> 3. which tells us that <hi>the Law was weak through the fleſh;</hi> that is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to juſtifie us, in regard of our inability (through corruption) to fulfill it which were untrue, if we are able to fulfill it; and what follows, <hi>God ſent his own Son</hi> to give us what we could not attain to by our own obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Law; and as for the 4th <hi>v.</hi> it imports the end for which God ſent Chriſt, that the righteouſneſſe of the Law might be fulfilled in us; not in our own perſons, but in Chriſt, his righteou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>neſſe imputed to us, as if it had been inherent in our ſelves.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. <hi>Fiſher.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>That is thy meaning, but not the meaning of the Apoſtle.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:124811:14"/>
               <speaker>T. Danſon.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, but it is the Apoſtles, as I have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. But pray Sir, let me ask you a queſtion (though it may ſeem beſides, yet it will be to the purpoſe) 'tis this: whether there be any true believers who are not perfect?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſher.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>I muſt acknowledg that there are degrees a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong believers, as the Apoſtle ſaies, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.13, 14. <hi>Little children, Fathers, Young men.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. Danſon.</speaker>
               <p>I ſuppoſe you mean, that ſome of theſe have a mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ture of ſin with their Grace. But let me ask you but one queſtion more, whether the children (for inſtance b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in a juſtified eſtate or not?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. <hi>Fiſher,</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>I'le tell thee <hi>Tho. Danſon,</hi> there are but two eſtates. Juſtification, and condemnation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. D.</speaker>
               <p>Now Sir, you are caught in a manifeſt contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction and abſurdity, for before you maintain'd that our juſtification was by a perſonal fulfilling of the Law, and now you grant ſome perſons to be juſtified who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver did fulfill it perſonally. That end I propoſed in ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you the queſtions, and I have obtain'd it to make your folly manifeſt to all men.
[Reader, obſerve that though it concern'd Mr. <hi>Fiſher</hi> to wind himſelf out of this contradiction, yet he did not reply, but ſate down on the top of the ſeat like a man aſtoniſh'd, and under the Hereticks judgement, I mean ſelf-condemned, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.11.] After a while we fell upon an Arminian point, whether a man that is juſtified may be unjuſtified? which Mr. <hi>Fiſher</hi> affirmed, and I would have omitted all the diſcourſe, but for the ſtrangeneſſe of one <hi>medium,</hi> by which he endeavoured to confirm it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. <hi>Fiſher.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>Take the inſtance of <hi>David,</hi> Pſalm 51.4. <hi>That thou mighteſt be juſtified when thou speakeſt, and clear when thou judgeſt.</hi> Whence I argue, if <hi>David</hi> was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtified in his own conſcience, he was unjuſtified before God, (and conſequently a man may become unjuſtified
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:124811:14"/> after he hath been juſtified before God) But <hi>David</hi> was unjuſtified in his own Conſcience, <hi>Ergo,</hi> he was ſo before God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. D.</speaker>
               <p>I might deny your <hi>minor,</hi> for it does not appear to me, that <hi>David</hi> was at this time unjuſtified in his own Conſcience, but the contrary, for he ſpake theſe words after the Prophet <hi>Nathan</hi> had come to him, <hi>Title of Pſ.</hi> 51. And we find, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.13. The Prophet told him, <hi>the Lord hath put away thy ſin.</hi> He might loſe much of his joy, and yet retain the ſenſe of his intereſt. And for the words, <hi>David</hi> either acknowledged Gods righteouſneſs in the temporal evils threatned againſt him, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12 11. or the deſert of condemnation. But I chuſe to deny your Sequel.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. <hi>Fiſher.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>I prove it, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.20. <hi>If our hearts condemn us, God is greater than our hearts, and knoweth all things.</hi> Here the Apoſtle argues to Gods condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, from that of our own hearts, which is alwayes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the light of the Spirit.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. Danſon.</speaker>
               <p>Your place proves nothing about <hi>Davids</hi> ſtate; but to take it as it comes, nor does it prove your aſſertion in the general; the place ſpeaks of ſuch a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence as is paſſed by a Conſcience not erroneous, but rightly guided. [I ſhall add to what was ſpoken, but theſe Scriptures againſt that tenent, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 77.8, 9, 10. <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.54. Compared with <hi>v.</hi> 44. <hi>T t.</hi> 1.15. <hi>Their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is defiled.</hi> Of which latter Scripture, I ſay but this, that one of Conſciences Offices being a <hi>Witneſſe,</hi> its defilement as ſuch<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in the wicked, is to lead them into a wrong opinion of their eſtares, and Conſcience in the Saints, being but in part cleanſed, as a witneſſe, it teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies falſhood to them alſo, in that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> eſtate is bad, when it is good, as to the wicked, that it is good, when it is nothing leſſe.]</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:124811:15"/>
            <head>An Account of a Diſcourſe <hi>April</hi> 13 be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween three QUAKERS, Mr. <hi>S. Fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, G. Whitehead, R. Hubberthorn,</hi> and <hi>T. Danſon.</hi>
            </head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. D.</speaker>
               <p>Mr. <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſher,</hi> becauſe you urged ſo hard for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Conference, I have granted your deſire, yet not for your ſake, ſo much as the hearers, that they may be convinced of the damnableneſſe of your Doctrine, and may loath and deteſt you, as you well deſerve. And againſt it, I ſhall urge one irrefragable Scripture, which I ſhould be glad to hear your anſwer to, or elſe you ſhall oppoſe, and I will anſwer, which I rather deſire: The place is, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.6. <hi>And if by Grace, then it is no more of works, otherwiſe Grace is no more Grace. But if it be of works, then it is no more of Grace, otherwiſe work is no more work.</hi> The Apoſtle having ſpoken of the efficient cauſe of Election, and effectual calling, he here excludes works from being any cauſe of them. And this he does by an argument taken from the oppoſition between im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate contraries: And I apply it to the caſe in hand, thu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, that if Juſtification be of wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ks, as you aſſert, then Grace is excluded from any hand in Juſtification, which is contrary to the Scripture, which ſays, <hi>we are Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by Grace.</hi> Our Juſtification cannot be a debt and a free gift, I mean not both in reſpect of us. [To this no reply was made.]</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. D.</speaker>
               <p>I will name another Scripture, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.3.4.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:124811:15"/> 
                  <hi>For they being ignorant of Gods righteouſneſs, and going about to establiſh their own righteouſneſs, have not ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted themſelves to the righteouſneſſe of God. For Christ is the end of the Law for righteouſneſs to every on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</hi> The Apoſtle here makes a diſtinction between our own righteouſneſſe and Gods, and finds fault with them, who neglect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng Gods, went about to eſtabliſh their own. And be makes our own righteouſneſſe to be a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal conformity to the Law, and Gods righteouſneſſe to be Chriſt made ours by faith, you are therefore guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of this ſin, who make your own righteouſneſs your ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. Whitehead.</speaker>
               <p>We do not make our own righteouſneſſe our juſtification, but the righteouſneſſe of God is that we teſtifie, being made manifeſt in us.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. D.</speaker>
               <p>Do not ye delude your hearers with doubtful words? Ye did yeſterday aſſert that the righteouſneſſe which we are enabled to perform, or our good works are the meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious cauſe of our juſtification.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. Whithead.</speaker>
               <p>We witneſſe to the righteouſneſſe of God according to the Scripture, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.9. <hi>Not having mine own righteouſneſs which is of the Law, but that which is through the Faith of Chriſt, the righteouſneſs which is of God by Faith.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. D.</speaker>
               <p>You could not have brought a Scripture more full againſt you. The righteouſneſs which is of Chriſt, and of God by Faith, is cal'd Chriſt, <hi>verſ.</hi> 8. <hi>That I may win Chriſt.</hi> And how he is our righteouſneſs, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>ult.</hi> tells us, as Chriſt was made ſin for us, ſo are we the righteouſneſs of God in him, but the former was by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, not inherence, and therefore ſo the other. So that the Apoſtle by his <hi>own righteouſneſs</hi> underſtands his perſonal conformity to the Law, and by <hi>Chriſts righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> that which is in Chriſt, made his by Faith.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. Whithead.</speaker>
               <p>Then it ſeems you make two righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:124811:16"/> of Chriſt, whereas the righteouſneſs of Chriſt is but one.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. D.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, ſo I do, what of that? Do you think that the ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eouſneſs which the Apoſtle calls his own, was not Chriſts? Had he any righteouſneſs which he had not received? and yet that righteouſneſs which was in the Apoſtle, never was in Chriſt as the ſubj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct, but was wrought in him by Chriſt, as an efficient cauſe. And Chriſt had an inherent righteouſneſs, in reſpect of which he is ſaid to know no ſin, and to be a Lamb with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpot and blemiſh. Are not here then two righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes? and they ſerve for two different ends, the one for our juſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ation, the other for our ſanctification; the one gives us a right to the inheritance of the Saints in light, and the other makes us meet for poſſeſſion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>G W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>itehead.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>Let me ask thee a queſtion then, are not we juſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fied by Chriſt within us?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T.D.</speaker>
               <p>I anſwer, no, but by Chriſt without us.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>G W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>itehead.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>If we are not juſtified by Chriſt within us, then by another Chriſt, and ſo thou preacheſt two Chriſts, whereas Chriſt is not divided, and thou doſt that which thou chargeſt upon us, preach another Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. D.</speaker>
               <p>I did foreſee the catch you intended <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n your que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, and anſwered you the more careleſly, that I might ſee how you could improve your ſuppoſed advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage by i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. But now I will anſwer you more punctually. The Scripture by <hi>Chriſt w thin us,</hi> underſtand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rſon of Chriſt, but h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s operat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ons, the cauſe is put for the effect by a Metonymy (a word too hard for your ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ty) Compare <hi>Col.</hi> 1.26. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r ſt in you,</hi> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.17. <hi>That Christ m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y dwell in your hearts by Faith.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it follows not that we make two Chriſts. For we acknowledge that one and the ſame perſon juſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s us by a righteouſneſs inherent in himſelf, and ſanct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fies us by
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:124811:16"/> a righteouſneſſe which he works in us by his Spirit. So that when I deny juſtification by Chriſt within us, howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the words may ſound to your ears, yet to the judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous the meaning is obvious <hi>(viz.)</hi> that we deny our juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication by that righteouſneſſe in us, whereof Chriſt is the author, but not that I make two Chriſts. Two things are indeed expreſſed by the name of Chriſt, his perſon, and his operations in us, and I deny the latter, but aſſert the former for our righteouſneſſe to juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
[The Scripture ſpeaks of two Chriſts, Chriſt perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, and Chriſt myſtical, if I ſhould ſay, not Chriſt myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, but Chriſt perſonal is our Saviour, would you not ſpeak wiſely think you, to ſay, oh you make two Chriſts. This diſtinction you may find, <hi>Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſt pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſonal, Col.</hi> 2.8, 9.—<hi>not after Chriſt. For in him dwelleth all the fulneſſe of the Godhead bodily. Chriſt myſtical,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.12. <hi>As the body is one, and hath many members,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſo is Chriſt;</hi> meaning the Church, which <hi>v.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7. he calls the <hi>body of Chriſt.]</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. VVhitehead.</speaker>
               <p>I will prove by the Scriptures that we are juſtified by our ſanctification, whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h thou ſaieſt does but make us meet, not give us a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itle, which thou ſhalt ſee it does to the i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heritance, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.32. <hi>And now Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, I commend you to God, and to the word of his grace, which is able to build you up, and to give you an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance among all them which are ſanctified.</hi> Gods grace gives an inheritance. [Here there was ſome diſturbance among the people, which occaſioned <hi>VVhiteheads</hi> addreſſe to them, and though I call'd to him often to take an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, he would not; but at length Mr. <hi>Fiſher</hi> ſtarted up, and urged another Scripture, and ſo this was omitted; to it therefore I ſhall now return a brief anſwer, That the Participle <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, cannot refer to grace as this man would have it, (or if it did, yet grace in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ends not ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification, but the favour of God, which is the ſubject
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:124811:17"/> matter of the word which the Apoſtle cals, <hi>v.</hi> 24. <hi>the Goſpel of the Grace of God</hi>) but it refers to <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> God, and ſhould be read, who is able, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſo it is nothing to his purpoſe.]</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. <hi>Fiſher.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>I will prove we are juſtified by grace or ſanctification, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.7. <hi>that being juſtified by his grace, we ſhould be made heirs according to the hope of eternal l fe.</hi> The grace by which we are ſaid to be juſtified, is the ſame with that which is called <hi>waſhing of regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and renewing of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> v. 5.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. D.</speaker>
               <p>You are much miſtaken Sir, the grace <hi>v.</hi> 7. is not meant of ſanctification, but of the favour of God, which is manifeſted in the donation of his Son to us, imputation of his r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ghteouſneſſe, and acceptance of us as righteous in him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. VVhitehead.</speaker>
               <p>I ſhall prove that we are juſtified by Faith as the cauſe of our juſtification, by the plain words of the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom</hi> 4.3. <hi>Abraham believed God, and it was counted to him for righteouſneſs.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. D.</speaker>
               <p>But pray obſerve how well this agrees with your former Doctrine, that we are juſtified by a perſonal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to the whole Law, and now you will prove that a conformity to one part will ſuffice. You interferr and cut one leg againſt t'other, and are not ſenſible of it, Does not the Apoſtle oppoſe Faith and Works? Now if Faith be conſidered as a work, there's no oppoſition be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them. And does not that oppoſition exclude Faith as a work? Yes ſurely; and is boaſting excluded in juſtification by Faith as a work? no but there is more ground of boaſting in the vertue of Faith, were that equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent to univerſal obedience. Read <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.27. <hi>Where is boaſting then? it is excluded. By what Law? of works? nay but by the Law of Faith;</hi> and <hi>chap.</hi> 4.5. <hi>To him that worketh not, but believeth,</hi> &amp;c. which plainly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mates, that Faith is oppoſed to it ſelf as a work, in the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:124811:17"/> buſineſſe of Juſtification; and as for the words of the Text, the act is put for the object to which it relates, as if it had be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n in expreſſe terms. Chriſt whom his Faith laid hold upon, was imputed to him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or righteouſneſſe; But that Faith is imputed to us, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng nſtead of a perfect righteouſneſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> perſonal, or that 'tis the meritori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous cauſe of our juſtification; I utterly deny.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>G. Wh.</speaker>
               <p>Thou doſt darken counſel by words without knowledge; and perverteſt the Scripture by thy mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. D.</speaker>
               <p>That's your uſual charge, but I deny it; the Scriptures attribute our juſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fication to the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, in the ſame ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y deny it to works. Receiving of Chriſt, and remiſſion of ſins, is the Office of Faith, and not to merit them.
<gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> [Here we fell into a diſcourſe very abruptly, about ſeveral Armini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an points, which for the Reaſons mentioned in the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, I omit.]</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>An Account of a Diſcourſe <hi>April</hi> 19th. between two Quakers, <hi>Mr. FISHER, R. HUBBERTHORN,</hi> AND <hi>THOMAS DANSON.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe firſt Queſtion debated on was, <hi>Whether the Scriptures are the VVord of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. D.</speaker>
               <p>Mr. <hi>F.</hi> You promiſed to diſcourſe upon this Queſtion, I deſire to know what you hold about it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. <hi>F.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>if you mean by the Scripture the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:124811:18"/> or the paper and ink, we deny it to be the Word of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. D</speaker>
               <p>Sir you cannot believe us ſo ſimple (ſurely) as to affirm the Scriptures in that ſenſe the Word of God, but we mean the matter contained in the writing, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that be our rule of faith and life.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. <hi>F.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>This I affirm, that there are ſeveral Books which are as much a rule (as thoſe you call the Scripture) which are not bound up in your Bibles.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. D.</speaker>
               <p>This is not to the purpoſe, yet I ſhould be glad to hear your proof.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. F.</speaker>
               <p>1 Cor. 5.9. I <hi>wrote unto you in an Epiſtle,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>But now I have written unto you,</hi> v. 11. Here you find an Epiſtle of <hi>Paul,</hi> which was written before this which in your books is called the firſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. D.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, you fall ſhort in your proof, you ſhould prove that the Epiſtle there mentioned was intended as much for our rule, as theſe we have in our books, and you prove only that ſuch an Epiſtle was written by <hi>Paul.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. <hi>F.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>If this Epiſtle was written to the ſame end with this you have, <hi>viz.</hi> to inſtruct the <hi>Corinthians</hi> how to carry themſelves toward groſſe ſinners, then it was inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded as much for a rule as this; But it was written to the ſame end, <hi>Ergo.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. D.</speaker>
               <p>I deny your conſequence; Sermons, private re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious diſcourſes have the ſame common end with the written Scriptures, yet the latter only are our ſtanding-rule, the former our rule, but ſo farre as they agree with the latter in the Scriptures.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. <hi>F.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>VVhat other evidence or character have you of this Epiſtles being a rule, which the other wants, that is not in your books.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. D.</speaker>
               <p>Pray let me ask you one Queſtion, and I will anſwer yours. Have you or any of your friends this firſt
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:124811:18"/> Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> or do you know that it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. <hi>F.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>No.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. D.</speaker>
               <p>Then I have a ſignal diſtinction between that and theſe we have, <hi>viz.</hi> that God hath preſerved theſe two for our uſe, but not the firſt, whereas had God inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the firſt for a ſtanding rule to us, as he hath the other two, his providence which watched over theſe, would alſo have watched over that.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. <hi>F.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>But I will give you an inſtance of a Book which ye have not, but we have, <hi>Col.</hi> 4.16. <hi>And that ye likewiſe read the Epiſtle from Laodicea.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T D.</speaker>
               <p>Though it is certain that God intended not that for a ſtanding rule, which is loſt yet all that was written by holy men, and preſerved for our uſe, is not therefore our ſtanding rule, for then the diſcourſes of holy Miniſters in former and latter times ſhould be our Rule, which they are not, but to be brought to the written Word, as the Rule and Teſt. But pray Sir, what is the Title of that Epiſtle you have?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. <hi>Fiſher.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>The Epiſtle of <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Laodiceans.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. D.</speaker>
               <p>So I thought; ſuch an Epiſtle I know there is that go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s under the name of <hi>Paul,</hi> but the place you bring ſpeaks not of an Epiſtle to <hi>Laodice<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> but from <hi>Laodicea:</hi> And for ought you can prove to the contrary, we have the Epiſtle <hi>Paul</hi> did intend, 1 <hi>Tim. Poſtſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ipt. The firſt to Timothy was written from Laodicea.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. Fiſher.</speaker>
               <p>Doſt thou own the Poſtſcripts to be Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical (as ye call it.)</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. D.</speaker>
               <p>As Canonical for ought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ppears yet to me, as your Epiſtle to the Laodiceans. W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> know well enough that your Brethren of the Popiſh party, have laid many ſuch brats at the Apoſtles doors, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch they will not fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And you ſhew what you a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, in abetting their wickedneſs. [I ſhall add, that ſome learned men judge
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:124811:19"/> that Epiſtle mentioned from <hi>Laodicea, Col.</hi> 4.16. to be not an Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtle written by <hi>Paul</hi> either from or to <hi>Laodicea,</hi> but by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Laodiceans,</hi> to <hi>Paul,</hi> which he would have read amon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>Colloſſians,</hi> that they might underſtand the caſe of their Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Church, and how ſutable the matter of the Epiſtle to them, was alſo to the <hi>Laodiceans. Vid. Rev. Daven. in locum.</hi>] And to make the buſineſſe ſhort, Mr. <hi>Fiſher,</hi> ſuppoſe we ſhould grant you there were ſuch an Epiſtle legitimate, yet it will not follow that it was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for a rule to us. For we have already as much as God thought ſufficient, read <hi>John</hi> 20.30, 31. <hi>And ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other ſigns truely did Jeſus in the preſence of his Diſciples, which are not written in this book, but theſe are written that ye m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ght believe,</hi> &amp;c. Suppoſe that we had the ſigns which are not in the Goſpel, faithfully recorded in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, yet were they not our Rule, becauſe God did not give order for them, but has aſſured us as much as is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to create and preſerve Faith in the Goſpel which we have. Let us come to the Queſtion, which I propoſe to you in theſe terms, <hi>Whether the Books commonly called the Old and New Teſtament, were appointed by God for a ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Rule of Faith and life?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. <hi>Fiſher.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>I deny thoſe books to be a ſtanding Rule of Faith and life.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. D.</speaker>
               <p>Now you have ſpit your venom, which I knew you were big with. And I will ſay to you (as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle) If any man bring any other Goſpel than what we have received, let him be accurſed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr <hi>Fiſher.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>I am ſure the Goſpel you preach will never bring men to heaven. Indeed people it will not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. D.</speaker>
               <p>Then friends, you hear his acknowledgement, and how well he deſerves the curſe denounced againſt him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. F.</speaker>
               <p>If there be another ſtanding Rule, then the Scripture is not it, but there is another ſtanding Rule,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:124811:19"/> therefore the Scripture is not it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. D.</speaker>
               <p>I deny your <hi>Minor;</hi> there is no other ſtanding rule but the Scripture.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. <hi>Fiſher.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>I prove there is, from <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.16. <hi>This I ſay then, walk in the ſpirit:</hi> We are commanded to walk in or by the Spirit, and therefore that is our rule. The Scripture it ſelf ſends us to another for our rule.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. <hi>D.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>That phraſe does note the principle, not the rule of our obedience in that place.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. <hi>F.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>You ſuppoſe the Letter to be antecedent to the Spirit, whereas the Spirit is antecedent to the Letter, and none can walk in the Letter, till they walk in the Spirit.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. D.</speaker>
               <p>The Spirit is antecedent to the Letter in reſpect of the revelation of the Letter, but the Spirit is ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent to the Letter in reſpect of aſſiſtance and ability which he gives to obedience. And whereas you affirm, none can walk in the Letter, till they walk in the Spirit, if walking in the Spirit be meant of ſpecial aſſiſtance 'tis falſe, for many walk in many things according to the Letter, without the Spirits in-dwelling, as <hi>Paul,</hi> while a Phariſee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> was <hi>touching the righteouſneſse of the Law blameleſse,</hi> Phil. 3.6.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. <hi>F.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>I will prove the Lette<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the Scripture is not our Rule: if there was a rule before the Scripture was written, then that is not our rule; but there was a rule before the Scripture, Therefore.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. D.</speaker>
               <p>Your Argument concludes nothing againſt us, for we aſſert the matter contained in the Scripture is a ſtanding Rule, your argument proves but that there was a rule before this writing, we grant that God reveal'd himſelf by viſions, dreams, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet it was the ſame matter: Since the Goſpel preached to <hi>Adam,</hi> there have not been any increaſe of truths <hi>quoad eſſentiam, ſed tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum quoad explicationem</hi> (as the Learned ſpeak of the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:124811:20"/> Articles of our Faith) The manner of conveyance is dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent then and now, but the matter or doctrines con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed ſtill the ſame. All this while you go about to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude the ſimple, as if you denied only this way of writing to have always been the onely way of conveyance, and you magnifie the Spirit, that with more ſecurity you may throw down the Letter of the Scripture. And if you would ſpeak out plainly, as ſome of your friends (as you call them do) that which you call the <hi>Spirit</hi> would be found to be the dictates of your own Conſcience (blind and corrupt, as they are the Lord knows) and you are no further bound to obey the Letter of the Scripture than you are willing to obey it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. <hi>F.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>I am ſure your Scripture is not the Word of God, for that is within, but your Scripture is without. This I prove out of <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m.</hi> 10.8. <hi>The Word is nigh thee, even in thy heart.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. D.</speaker>
               <p>You read not all, 'tis <hi>in thy mouth too,</hi> ſo that 'tis without as well as within.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. <hi>F.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>This is meant of the Light which is in eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y mans Conſcience. 'Tis a word which every man ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h heard, <hi>v.</hi> 18. <hi>But I ſay have they not heard? yes verily, their ſound went into all the earth.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. D.</speaker>
               <p>It ſeems then the Light within is <hi>the Spirit</hi> you pleaded for to be the Rule, in oppoſition to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. But 'tis plain enough that <hi>v.</hi> 18. ſpeaks of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, for it relates to the Preacher ſpoken of <hi>v.</hi> 14, 15. who were Prophets and Apoſtles. And though the words are taken out of <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.4. yet they intend not that n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al knowledge of God which <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks of, but the Apoſtle would intimate that the knowl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dge of Chriſt by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel ſhould be of as large extent in the publication, as the knowledge of God by the Miniſtry of the heavens and Firmament, which are <hi>Davids</hi> Preachers, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.1. And 'tis evident that the word ſpoken of in the heart,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:124811:20"/> 
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.8. is meant of the matters contained in the Scriptures, for the Apoſtle ſaies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xpreſly, <hi>That is the word of Faith which we preach,</hi> and <hi>Acts</hi> 26.22. <hi>VVe ſay none other things than thoſe which Moſes and the Prophets did ſay ſhould come;</hi> which ſayings are contained in the Old Teſtament. And as for your odd notion of the Words being within not without, I ſay but this, that it remains without when it is within, as the matter in a Book does to inſtruct others, when the Reader hath throughly digeſted it in his memory and unde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtanding. And that as to the Saints ſomewhat of the word is alwaies without, when ſome is within, that is, the Word pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vails but in part over their corruption, and ſo far as it does prevail, it is within, ſo far as it prevails not, it is without.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. <hi>F.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>In <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Let the word of Chriſt dwell in you richly;</hi> that which is the word of Chriſt dwells with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, whereas that which ye call the VVord is without.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. D.</speaker>
               <p>The VVord ſpoken of was without, or it was the Letter of the Scripture, and his exhortation was to get acquaintance therewith, and he preſcribes means to that end, in teaching and admoniſhing one another, and ſinging Pſalms which were part of the <hi>Word of Chriſt,</hi> as the ſubject matter and author of them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. <hi>F.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>Now thou talkeſt of ſing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng Pſalms, it is a fond cuſtom you get to make the people ſing <hi>Davids</hi> conditions, who have not his ſpirit, as to make a proud man ſing, <hi>O Lord I am not puff'd in mind.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. D.</speaker>
               <p>Though it be beſides our buſineſſe, yet I ſhall anſwer to your cavils againſt our practice in a word. Your objection holds as ſtrongly againſt the uſe of them in the times of the Old Teſtament, as againſt our uſe of them; for the matter of them was no more all the ſingers conditions then than now, and yet they were part of publique Temple-worſhip, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.25, 30. and the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:124811:21"/> matter of many of them is doctrinal, and prophetical, and ſuch as cannot be ſung with particular application; and I know no particular application neceſſary to ſinging that 131 <hi>Pſal.</hi> more than to reading of it, nor is it more a lye to ſing than to read them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr F.</speaker>
               <p>VVhereas thou ſayeſt <hi>Thomas Danſon</hi> that the teaching and ſinging was a means of the words dwelling in them; therein thou art out (as in many other things) for the word of Chriſt dwelt richly in them, and thence they teached, admoniſhed, and ſung.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. D.</speaker>
               <p>The words are an exhortation to get the word of Chriſt dwell richly in them, or to grow in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Chriſt (as elſewhere 'tis expreſſed) and there is none that hath ſo much of the knowledge of the word, but it may admit of encreaſe; and therefore though they might teach and admoniſh from a ſtock of the word, that hinders not but that the uſe of it in thoſe duties might be the means of adding to it.</p>
               <p>In the next place <hi>Richard Hubberthorn</hi> undertook to prove his <hi>Call</hi> in a diſcourſe wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch you have in his own Book, to which I referre you; the main thing he inſiſted on was his Infallibility in teaching, and the falſehood of our Miniſtry, who are not Infallible.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. D.</speaker>
               <p>You are much miſtaken in thinking you are infallible, it appears otherwiſe to us by the falſe doctrines which you teach; and as for your participation of the infallible Spirit (if that were granted, which we cannot grant) that infers not a participation of the ſpirits infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, for that is as incommunicable, as omniſciency or omnipotency.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>R. Hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>berthorn.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>The Apoſtles had a power of working miracles in them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. D.</speaker>
               <p>That i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nyed; God himſelf was the ſole ſubject of that power by which they were wrought, and their
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:124811:21"/> faith was the means or ſign of exerting it, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.16. <hi>His Name, through faith in his Name hath made this man strong,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Matth.</hi> 21.21. <hi>If ye have faith and doubt not,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ye ſhall ſay to this mountain be removed, and it ſhall be done.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. <hi>Fiſher.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>The man Chriſt Jeſus whom ye call God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, was omniſcient, <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.24. <hi>Jeſus did not commit himſelf to them, becauſe he knew all men,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>T. D.</speaker>
               <p>Pray ſir, Do not you call the man Chriſt Jeſus God-man too?—Your ſilence is not conſent, but diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. Omniſciency agreed not to Chriſt as man (for he ſays elſewhere, the ſon of man knows not when the day of judgement ſhall be) but as God. You know well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough what communication of Idioms means. And the Apoſtles themſelves did not partake of that divine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of Infallibility, for then they would have been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible at all times, and in all things, which they were not, as appears by the inſtance of <hi>Peter,</hi> Gal. 2.11. But in the delivery of what was to be a ſtanding rule to us, they were ſo guided that they d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d not erre, as you may find. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. ult. <hi>The prophecy came not in old time by the will of man, but holy men of God ſpake as they were moved by the holy Ghoſt.</hi>—As for our want of infallibility 'tis no valid plea againſt our Miniſtry, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.30. the Apoſtle ſpeaking to the <hi>Elders of Epheſus,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.17. <hi>Alſo of your own ſelves ſhall men ariſe, ſpeaking perverſe things, to draw away Diſciples after them.</hi> And yet he ſaies the holy Ghoſt had made theſe fallible men Overſeers over the Church, <hi>v.</hi> 28. 1 Thef. 5. <hi>Quench not the Spirit,</hi> verſ. 19. <hi>Deſpiſe not prophecying,</hi> verſ. 20. <hi>Prove all things, hold faſt that which is good,</hi> v. 21. The connexion of theſe verſes im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, that that prophecying muſt not be deſpiſed, nor can be, without neglecting the Spirit in it, which may teach us ſomewhat which is not good, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived. And both theſe inſtances are of an ordinary Miniſtry, which is ſet in the ſame univerſal Church with
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:124811:22"/> the extraordinary, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28. and for the ſame end, <hi>viz.</hi> to convert and build up, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.12. [Note that when we had gone thus far, I gave a brief account of my Call, for which you are referred to <hi>Hubberthorns</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Conference, and my anſwer hereto annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.]</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>A ſhort ANSWER to a trifling Pamphlet intituled, <hi>The Difference of that Call of God to the Miniſtry,</hi> &amp;c. pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by <hi>R. Hubberthorn.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IN the Epiſtle to the Reader, the Queſtions debated on are falſly ſtated, as will appear by the Narrative here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to annexed.</p>
            <p>In the Book it ſelf, you have his Call to the Miniſtry, which is not worthy a further Reply than I made by word of mouth. And an account of my Call, which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept two or three paſſages, was the ſumme of what I ſpake.</p>
            <p>One paſſage is, <hi>He ſaid, I ſaid 'tis non ſence to ſay that a man is made a Minister by the gift of grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> My words were, that he had ſpoken a great deal of non-ſence in his diſcourſe, not that that particular paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage was non ſenſe. Yet I ſaid, and do ſtill ſtand to it, that if by <hi>gift of grace</hi> he means qual<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fications for the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, more is r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>quired to a miſſion than them.</p>
            <p>Another paſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge is, <hi>That I ſaid, my qualifications were ſuch, that I might have been cloathed in Scarlet.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:124811:22"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> I ſaid not ſo of my ſelf particularly, but in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, that many of us who had choſen the Miniſtry for our calling, were capable of other callings, and had opportunities of entring into them, which might have cloathed us with ſcarlet, as they did other men who fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed them.</p>
            <p>VVhereas he ſaies, that <hi>T. D. provoked his Church to laughter, rudeneſs, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> I confeſs the Aſſembly did laugh oftentimes at their ſorry ſhifts, and poor evaſions in our diſcourſe, but that I did compoſe them, I have many witneſſes: And I deny not but that now and then I could not forbear ſmiling at them, which I preſume as juſtifiable in me, as <hi>Elijah</hi> the Prophets ſcoffing at <hi>Bauls</hi> Prieſts, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.27.</p>
            <p>Whereas he ſayes, that <hi>none of my people can ſet to their ſeal that my Miniſtry hath brought them to a perfect man,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> 'Tis readily granted, nor was the Miniſtry in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for that end, but only to br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng the Saints to that degree of Grace in this life, which might make them im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly capable of perfection in the next life</p>
            <p>Note that <hi>R. H.</hi> brings in ſeveral paſſages as mine, ſome of which I own, and others which I own not, I ſhall name them briefly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That every individual man is not enlightened by Chriſt;</hi> and he complaines that I brought two meanings of that Scripture, and know not which is the meaning of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> I ſtill affirm the Propoſition mentioned; and I would have him to know, that both the meanings are the Holy Ghoſts, though but one is intended in that place: the phraſes will bear either ſenſes, and either of them croſs his Interpretation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the whole body of the Gentiles was not enlightned.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:124811:23"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> He leaves out what I added, <hi>viz.</hi> by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or with the knowledg of ſalvation. As for his anſwer, I refer you to the diſpu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e upon that principle.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the Gospel is an external Light, and not inviſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le, and that it is not the Light within.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> My wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ds were that the Goſpel is an external L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght, as that of the Sun, and that there is an inward Light created in the ſoul (c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll'd an underſtanding g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ven us <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.20.) which is as the Light in the eye; and that the light of the Goſpel is not the light which every man naturally hath with in him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That Chriſt is a propitiation but for the world of believers intend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d,</hi> 1 John 2.2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> I expla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n'd my meaning when I ſo interp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eted the ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſe, by c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mparing it with <hi>Rom.</hi> 3 25. <hi>Whom God hath ſet for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h to be a Propitiation through Faith in his blood;</hi> the ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſe Prop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tiation intends not the price, but the actual atton<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ment, and this latt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r is not without the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervention of Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th: So th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t <hi>John</hi> intends as <hi>Paul,</hi> that the terms of actual reconciliation w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th God are the ſame to all the world, <hi>viz.</hi> beli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ving in the blood of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at we muſt reconcile Scriptures,</hi> and he ſaies I gave two contrary meanings of one Scripture.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> I have ſaid enough to this in the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſpute, the Scriptures are not at variance among themſelves, but they ſ em ſo to be, and 'tis part of our wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k to l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ople ſee how well they are agreed. And I dare leave it to any Reade<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dgement, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h r theſe two interpretations which R. H. intends be contrary to one another, <hi>viz.</hi> that Chriſt enl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ghtens every man who is <hi>(ſpi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itually)</hi> enlightened, or that he enlightens a number of every Nation, which were the two meanings (to uſe his phraſe) of <hi>John</hi> 1.8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the Law of the Spirit of life in Chriſt, was not the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:124811:23"/> Law of the Spirit in the Saints, but that they were two Laws,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> My words were, that by the Law of the Spirit of life in Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8 2. was not meant our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal righteouſn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe, but Chriſts imputed to us, and that though the righteouſneſſe in Chriſt, and in us, are of the ſame kind yet they have not the ſame uſe, the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer being alone our juſtification, the latter our ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That there are two righteouſneſſes of Chriſt, the one with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Saints to juſtifie them, and the other within the Saints, that did ſanctifie them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> My words were, that there is a righteouſneſs whereof Chriſt is the ſubject and the efficient (<hi>viz.</hi> that of his Humane Nature) and a righteouſneſſe whereof he is the efficient, but not the ſubject, nor was it ever for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally exiſtent in him (as the ſpirits were in the brain, which are communicated thence to other parts of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy) and that is the righteouſneſſe in the Saints, and that theſe are two righteouſneſſes (though of one ſpecies) in reſpect of the ſubjects, and uſe of them.</p>
            <p>That I denyed, that <hi>the Saints were justified by that Chriſt hat was in them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply</hi> I may ſay to thee, <hi>R. H.</hi> as <hi>David</hi> to <hi>Doeg, Thou lovest lying rather than to ſpeak righteouſneſs, Pſal.</hi> 52.3. I denyed that the Saints are juſtified by Chriſt within them (<hi>i. e.</hi> by the works of Chriſt within them, which have in that phraſe the name of the efficient gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to them by a metonymy) but not that they are juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by that Chriſt that was in them; and when one of the Quakers prated to the ſame purpoſe with this man, that I made two Chriſts, I expreſly told him my mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be not by Chriſt as in the Saints; but as far were the words from my mouth, as the thoughts from my heart, to ſay that it was not one and the ſame Chriſt that juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies and ſanctifies.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:124811:24"/>
            <p>That <hi>David when he was guilty of adultery and murder, was not in a condemned ſtate, but in a juſtified eſtate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> I grant the whole, and have ſaid more for the proof of it, than this man or any of his Brethren can an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</p>
            <p>That <hi>I ſaid the paſſage</hi> Heb. 12.23. <hi>Spirits of juſt men made perfect, was meant of them in Heaven, not on earth;</hi> which ſaies <hi>R. H.</hi> cannot be, becauſe the Apoſtle wrote to them on earth, and did not write to men after they were deceaſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> The Apoſtle intends, that 'tis the priviledge of the Saints on earth, who are unperfect, to be one body and ſociety with them in Heaven, who are perfect, and this he might ſay, though the perſons he wrote to were living.</p>
            <p>That <hi>any creature that holds that principle of being Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by a righteouſneſs within, living and dying in that principle, cannot come to Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And againſt this <hi>R. H.</hi> urges that Chriſt is the Juſtifier of them that believe, and his Doctrine is <hi>I in them, and they in me,</hi> ſo Chriſt and his Righteouſneſſe is in the Saints.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> Put in <hi>any man</hi> inſtead of <hi>any Creature</hi> which was not my phraſe, and add to <hi>within,</hi> but <hi>us,</hi> and I acknowledge the whole ſentence, and to your argument from the union between Chriſt and the Saints, I ſay but this, that if it makes us to be the ſubject of whatever Chriſt was the ſubject, becauſe he is <hi>in us,</hi> then I hope it will make Chriſt the ſubject of whatever we are, becauſe <hi>we are in him:</hi> and then Chriſt is a ſinner by inherent defilement, (unleſſe all who are united to him, be from the fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt moment of that union free from ſin) which is a Doctrine as falſe as falſhood can make it.</p>
            <p>That <hi>that which fitted men for the inheritance of the Saints in Light, did not entitle to the inheritance,</hi> which
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:124811:24"/> ſaies <hi>R. H.</hi> is contrary to the Apoſtles Doctrine, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.12. And the Father both fitted them for the inheritance, and did entitle and give them a part in the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> See the baſeneſs of this man, he would make the Reader believe, that I denied the <hi>Fathers</hi> giving right and poſſeſſion, and making meet for it, when as I ſpake of things, not of perſons, of the cauſe of our title, and of that which made us meet for poſſeſſion (without which Heaven would not be a place or ſtate of bliſſe) and that the righteouſneſſe in Chriſt as a ſubject, was the cauſe of our title, and the righteouſneſſe wrought in us by Chriſt, makes us meet for poſſeſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That we cannot contain an infinite righteouſneſs in us.</hi> To which <hi>R. H.</hi> replies, then you cannot contain the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of God, for it is infinite, and then you cannot contain Chriſt in you, who is Gods righteouſneſſe, and who is infinite.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> The righteouſneſſe whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h God works in us, is but finite, as well as other effects, and the myſtical union between Chriſt and the Saints by Faith, does no more conclude their participation of incommunicable attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes, than the hypoſtatical union between Chriſts hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane and Divine Nature does infer that what was before ſuch union proper to one, ſhould be common to both natures; as Omnipotency, Omniſcience to the humane, weakneſs, mortality to the Divine Nature.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That it was falſe Doctrine to ſay that a man must firſt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of the righteouſneſs which justifies, before it can be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to him as his.</hi> To which <hi>R. H.</hi> replies, that the Saints did partake of Gods righteouſneſs through Faith, except that this Dr. would count that to be a mans, which he hath no right to, nor part in.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> Mark the juggling of this fellow, who would intimate that I denied a participation of Gods righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:124811:25"/> through Faith, when as that was the thing I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for, and which they denied, that we did partake of Gods righteouſneſſe by Faith to juſtification. That which I affirmed to be falſe Doctrine, was, that the righteouſneſſe which juſtifies is in us, and I aſſerted that we being juſtified by the righteouſneſs of another, there can be no way of conveying ſuch ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hteouſneſſe, but by imputation, and thereby the benefit of anothers righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe may redound to us, as if we were the ſubjects of it.</p>
            <p>That <hi>God offers ſalvation to all men, but he intends it onely to a few,</hi> which Doctrine ſaies <hi>R. H.</hi> makes the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers to no purpoſe to thouſands, and is a belying of God, and makes God a reſpecter of perſons, and how then is Chriſt given to be ſalvation to the ends of the earth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> I did not affirm that God offers ſalvation to all men, for many ages and generations never had one offer of it, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. <hi>laſt.</hi> The Apoſtle makes Chriſt <hi>preached to the Gentiles,</hi> one part of the <hi>myſtery of godlineſs;</hi> but I affirmed, and do, among thoſe who hear the Goſpel, ſalvation is offered to more than to whom it is intended. And as for your cavils, I anſwered them in my diſcourſe with Mr. <hi>Fiſher:</hi> The offer is to ſome purpoſe, to the ſame with natural light <hi>(viz.)</hi> to leave men <hi>without excuſe,</hi> Rom. 1.20. So that they cannot ſay (as we may ſuppoſe Heathens might) had we known of a remedy for our miſery, we would have uſed it; and to other purpoſes, but one inſtance ſhall ſuffice; you bely our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, in ſaying
'tis a belying of God, for God does not pretend, to intend the benefit offered to all to whom it is offered, <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m.</hi> 11.7. <hi>The El<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ction hath obtained it, and the reſt were blinded.</hi> And beſides, he offers it to all upon condition of acceptance, and could you ſuppoſe that all would take him at his word, and accept his offer, they
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:124811:25"/> ſhould have the benefit thereof. And this laſt anſwer will ſuffice (though other conſiderations might be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded) to that Objection of making God a reſpecter of perſons. Did God give ſalvation to ſome who accept not of it out of particular fancy to them, but exact of others that acceptance, and for default of it deny them ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then there might be ſome ground for the cavil; but now that 'tis offered upon equal terms, there is none. And for Chriſt being given for ſalvation to the ends of the earth, that imports not ſo much as that the offer, much leſſe the benefit ſhould be of ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h extent in all ages and generations (as I ſhewed before) but the fulfilling of that prophecy bears date from the Apoſtolical Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. and it intends that no Nation how re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote ſoever from <hi>Judea,</hi> ſhould want the offer, nor ſome of it the benefit of ſalvation.</p>
            <p>That <hi>a Miniſter of the Goſpel doth not know who are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected.</hi> And to this R. H. ſays, there he hath belied the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpel, for they could diſcern the elect from the world, as 'tis written, <hi>Ye ſhall diſcern between him that ſerveth God, and him that ſerveth him not,</hi> and theſe Teachers who know not the elect, and yet exhort all their hearers to believe, their preaching is in vain.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> I ſee you are hard put to it for a Scripture, to bring that <hi>Mal.</hi> 3. <hi>ult.</hi> I could have fitted you with one that would have been more ſpecious, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.4. <hi>Knowing Brethren beloved your Election of God.</hi> As for <hi>Mal.</hi> 3. <hi>ult.</hi> 'tis not ſtrictly true till the day of judgement: <hi>Solomon</hi> ſays, <hi>No man knows love or hatred by all that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him.</hi> I ſhould rather think our preaching is to more purpoſe becauſe we know not who are elect, for the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of that gives us a ground to hope well of any man; and indeed it were to no purpoſe to preach to thoſe who are not elected (unleſſe that of leaving them inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable) did we certainly know who are elect, and ſo
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:124811:26"/> who are not, for the latter would have no ground of hope (which now they have in the indefinite promiſe, made of none effect through their unbelief) did we let them know they were excluded out of Gods purpoſe of ſalvation.</p>
            <p>That <hi>the ſword of the Spirit is ineffectual without the Letter.</hi> To which <hi>R. H.</hi> ſays the ſword of the Spirit is the Word of God, which was effectual before the Letter was.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> This man is ſo uſed to ſpeak non-ſenſe himſelf, that he can underſtand it as well or better than good ſenſe. I did not ſay as he relates, but that <hi>the Spirit was not wont to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ff ctual without the Letter,</hi> or that he wrought upon the ſouls of men in and by the Letter of the Word, and I gave that inſtance, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.17. <hi>Faith</hi> (which is the Spirits work) <hi>comes by hearing, and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the Word of God.</hi> As for what he ſayes, that the ſword of the Spirit is the <hi>Word of God,</hi> if he means like a man in his oppoſitions, he muſt mean Chriſt (who but once is called the <hi>Word of God) Rev.</hi> 19.13. And Chriſt cannot be intended, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.17. becauſe he is not the ſword of the Spirit, but the Spirit his ſword rather, for by the Spirit he works in the hearts of men, and therefore <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.3. he ſayes, <hi>My Spirit ſhall not alwayes ſtrive with man,</hi> which is meant of the holy Ghoſt, as will appear by comparing it with, <hi>Act.</hi> 7 51. where <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen</hi> tells the <hi>Jews, Ye do alwayes reſiſt the holy Ghost.</hi> Chriſt by the common operations of his Spirit ſtrives with men, and by the ſpecial operations thereof prevails with them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That there was no Scripture written, but what is extant, and in the Bible.</hi> Againſt which aſſertion <hi>R.</hi> H. produces the book of <hi>Nathan, Iddo,</hi> &amp;c. mentioned in the Bible, which he ſayes were written for the ſame end and uſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> It does not appear that any of the Books men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:124811:26"/> in the Old Teſtament and to which we are referr'd for further ſatisfaction in hiſtorical matters, were of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Inſpiration, but we may rather conclude, that the Holy Ghoſt mentioning no more of Hiſtory than was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for our Inſtruction, refers us for the reſt, which was not of the like neceſſity to books of humane original. And though they are the Books of Prophets, yet it follows not that they were divinely inſpir'd: For they might as well write from their own ſpirits, or upon humane credit, as ſometimes ſpeak from their own ſpirits, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.3. <hi>Nathan</hi> told <hi>David,</hi> when he ſpake of building a Temple, <hi>Go, do all that is in thine heart, for the Lord is with thee,</hi> whenas God for bad him by the ſame Prophet, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition is call'd, <hi>the word of the Lo d that came to Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than,</hi> v. 4.5. plainly enough intimating that the incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement he gave <hi>David</hi> before, was but the word of man. And indeed 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. <hi>laſt.</hi> ſpeaking of the motion of the Holy Ghoſt to write the Scriptures, ſeems to limit it to that which was intended for a <hi>ſure word of prophecy, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto we ſhould do well to take heed, &amp;c.</hi> v. 19.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That there was no Scripture appointed of God to be a Rule of Faith and manners, but what is bound up in the Bible.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> That was my aſſertion, and beſides what I ſpake I ſhall adde, that
'tis not enough, if it could be proved that other writings beſides thoſe we have were of Divine Inſpiration: For beſides ſuch Inſpiration, to make a Rule, is neceſſary Gods appointment of a writing to that end. Hence 'tis obſervable that <hi>John</hi> is bidden to write what he ſaw and heard in the Book of <hi>Revelation,</hi> no leſſe than twelve times; and ſome things of the like inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he was forbidden to write, becauſe not intended for the ſame end, <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.4. <hi>And when the ſeven thunders had uttered th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir voices, I was about to write, and I heard a voice from Heaven ſaying unto me, ſeal up,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and write
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:124811:27"/> them not.</hi> John 20.30.31. <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d many other ſigns truly did Jeſus in the preſence of his Diſcipl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, which are not wri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ten in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his book, but theſe are written that ye might bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eve,</hi> &amp;c. Thoſe things which were not written might have b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en uſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ful if they had been wr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tten, for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y were done for the ſame end with tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e which are left u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, yet becauſe God thought that ſuffi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ient which we have, we can look upon no more wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h ſuch regard as we do upon that.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the letter doth antecede the Spirit in all that walked in the Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply</hi> I opened my own meaning (as you may find in the diſpute about the Scriptures,) and 'tis this, that the Spirits act of r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>veal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng the letter of the Scriptures, antecedes the Spirits aſſiſtance, in walking according to it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the works of Chriſt in ſome reſpect are not perfect.</hi> To which <hi>R. H.</hi> ſaies that is falſe, for <hi>every gift of God is perfect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> I ſpake thoſe words with reference to the work of ſanc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ification, which I affirmed to be imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rfect in this life, in compariſon of what it is in the life to come. For which I produced <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.12. <hi>Not as though I had already attained either, were already perfect,</hi> which he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntends of <hi>the reſurrection from the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad,</hi> v. 11. (as he calls the holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe of that ſtate by a Metonymy of the ſubject for the adj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nct.) I alſo quoted 1 <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or</hi> 13.10. <hi>When that which is perfect is come, then that which is in part ſhall be done away.</hi> And for the Scripture he quotes, intending I ſuppoſe, <hi>James</hi> 1.17. <hi>Every good and perfect gift is from above,</hi> are the words of the Holy Ghoſt, not every g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ft of God is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect; and I ſuppoſe 'tis ſpoken of ſpecial grace, which is ſtill in g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>owth; every leaſt degree of grace tending to perfection.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the Law requires more ſtrict and exact obedience then the Gospel.</hi> To whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h R. H. replies nay, the Law ſaith,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:124811:27"/> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt not commit adul ery,</hi> but the Goſpel ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt not luſt,</hi> &amp;c and ſo the Goſpel r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ires more ſtrict obedience than the Law.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> I ſpake thoſe words with reference to what the Law req<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ires of us, as 'tis a Covenan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of works, and to what the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l accepts of us as 'tis a Covenant of grace; though the Law g ves not life without perfect obedience, the Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pel gives it upon imperfect ob dience. The words were not intended of the Leg l and Ev ngelical diſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as <hi>R. H.</hi> ſeems to underſtand them in his Socinian interp etat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on. And as for his interpretation, I affirm that Chriſt intended not to adde any th ng to the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Law, for that under <hi>Moſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> was <hi>ſpiri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ual,</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks. <hi>Rom</hi> 7.14. for under the prohibition of the outward act, was alſo prohibit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d inward aff ct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ons, deſires, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch appears by Gods p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>omiſe, of <hi>ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cumciſing the heart, D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut</hi> 30.6. and his comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd to <hi>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſh their hearts from wick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that they might be ſav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d.</hi> But our Lord Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cates the Law from the cor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>upt gloſſes of the Phariſees, who interpreted thoſe proh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bitions to extend no fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther than the letter, which is but to the outward act, as w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll appear by the contex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, eſpecially <hi>v.</hi> 18.19.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt choſe a devil to be one of his Miniſters in chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Judas;</hi> and his pro f, ſaies R. H. was, <hi>That the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine nature did not ſee it good to commu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>icate the knowl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dg of all things to the hum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne nature, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>herefore al hough he was a devil when he choſe him, yet he k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ew it not,</hi> which ſaies R. H. is a charging of Chriſt with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gnorance, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to <hi>John</hi> 2.24 25. and Chriſt ſaies <hi>Judas</hi> had the ſpirit of the Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her in him <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t.</hi> 10.20.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply</hi> The oc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſion of my words was a little diſcourſe I had with Mr. <hi>F ſher</hi> about falling from grace; who urged that <hi>Judas</hi> had the Spirit of the Father in him, as well as the reſt. To which I anſwered, that ſeeing he appeared to be a devil in the end, he was ſo from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:124811:28"/> according to 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.19. ſpeaking of Chriſtians, <hi>They went out from us, but they were not of us; for if they had been of us, no doubt they would have continued with us; but they went out, that they might be made manifeſt that they were not all of us</hi> And that Chriſt ſpake ſo to him, becauſe he was a viſible Chriſtian; and it app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ars not that from the firſt moment of Chriſts choice he knew him to be a Devill, and thereupon I urged the principle above-named, and inſtanced in the Son of mans igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the day of judgement. But whether Chriſts humane Nature did know him or not, he was not open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcandalous, as appears by the Diſciples ſuſpition of themſelves rather than him, and therefore might be treated as one that had the Spirit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the Spirit of God may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccompany a Miniſtry, and the Miniſter not have the Spirit.</hi> Which <hi>R. H.</hi> ſaies he never read in the Scriptures, and bids me prove it when and where it was ſo at any time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> It is no great matter what you read in the Scriptures, for it appears by the diſpute about them, that you care not for them, but only to beat us (as you think) with our own weapon; and to obey your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, I have an inſtan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. <hi>The Scribes and P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ariſees ſit in Moſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ſeat, (i. e.</hi> ſuſtain the place of Teachers) <hi>all therefore whatſoever they bid you obſerve, that obſerve, and do; but do not ye after their works, for they ſay and do not,</hi> v. 2, 3. This command imports as much as the Apoſtle elſewhere expreſſes, <hi>viz. to obey from the heart the form of Doctrine which was delivered to them, Rom.</hi> 6.17. and to be ſure the Phariſees had not the ſpirit of holineſſe, though they had his bleſſing upon their Miniſtry.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the power that went forth in the Apoſtles Miniſtry, was in God, not in them, but as they have it communicated to them by the exerciſe of faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:124811:28"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> You abuſe me in the repetition of what I ſpake, either through ignorance or wilfulneſſe, for my words were, that the power by which the Apoſtles wrought Miracles, was not inherent in them, but that their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of Faith upon the promiſe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rting it for confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the Goſpel, was the ſign of the time when God put forth act, of Omn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>potency. This appears by the places before quot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.21. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cts</hi> 3.16. To which I add, <hi>v.</hi> 12. <hi>Why look ye ſo earneſtly on us, as though by our own power, or holineſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> we had made this man to walk?</hi> He calls the power their own, not in reſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct of the Original (for all things are of God) but in reſpect of the ſubject of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Rumſey</hi> ſaid, that we preach a Doctrine of Devils, in ſaying, <hi>that men may be free from ſin in this life.</hi> To which <hi>R.</hi> H. anſw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs that the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> then preached a Doct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ine of Devils, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.2, 7, 18, 22. And Chriſt preach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d the Doctrine of perfection, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.48. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.16. And <hi>Paul</hi> preached <hi>wiſdom among them that were perf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.6. And <hi>David</hi> pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ached that Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, <hi>Mark the perfect man,</hi> Pſal. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 37. Now <hi>David</hi> did not bid them mark ſuch a man as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>here was not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> You Quakers a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e an unmannerly Generation. You might have given a Magiſtrate the Title of Mr. As for Mr. <hi>Rumſey</hi>'s ſpeech he deſires me to let you know that he is confirm'd in his Opin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on, notwithſtanding the Scriptures you alledge (which being unlearned and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable, you wreſt to your own deſtruction) and he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires me to return you an anſwer to each. As for <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. The expreſſions of <hi>freed from ſin,</hi> do not note freedom from the being, but the dominion, <hi>verſ.</hi> 14. <hi>Sin ſhall not have dominion over you,</hi> v. 12. <hi>Let not ſin reign in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>our mortal bodies,</hi> &amp;c. And that it cannot be meant ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, will appear by <hi>c.</hi> 14.10. <hi>Why doſt thou judge thy Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? or why doſt thou ſet at nought thy Brother?</hi> The
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:124811:29"/> Apoſtle ſpeaks of judging as the ſin of weaker Chriſtians, and ſetting at nought his brother, as the ſin of ſtronger Chriſtians. And if ſin was conſiſtent with that <hi>freedom from ſin</hi> before affirmed of them, then the phraſe denotes not freedom from the being of ſin, as I have told you. As for <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. <hi>ult.</hi> The command intends the rule, not the degree of Grace attainable in this life, for this is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved for our reward in Heaven, (as I have proved in the diſpute) 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.16. urges Gods Holineſſe as an argument to enforce our endeavors after it; but that is no proof of your aſſertion. As for 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.6. I have already anſwered it in the diſpute And for <hi>Davids</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, the ſecond clauſe, <hi>and behold the upright,</hi> is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>egerical, or explanative of the firſt. Had <hi>David</hi> bid them <hi>mark a perfect man</hi> in your ſenſe, he had bid them mark a man that was not (as you ſpeak) for he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf was a <hi>Saul</hi> for ſpiritual ſtature in his generation (as appears, becauſe he is made a pattern to new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Saints, <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.8.) and yet he was not free from the being of ſin, but a ſad inſtance of the power of it in real Saints. But take the meaning of it as I have given, himſelf was one of the men he ſpake of.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:124811:29"/>
            <head>THE NARRATIVE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THou maiſt pleaſe to underſtand, that theſe Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, who like <hi>the Scribes and Phariſees, compaſſe ſea and land to make one Proſelyte,</hi> came to our Town, <hi>March</hi> 15, 1658. and made a challenge to the Prieſts (as they term Miniſters of Chriſt) to defend their own Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Call, which they came to oppugn; whereupon I was much urged by ſome good people, Inhabitants of the Town, to appear at their place of meeting, which at firſt I was ſomwhat unwilling to, partly becauſe I was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed that the men who intended to ſpeak were ſuch as the Apoſtle deſcribes, <hi>unreaſonable and wicked men,</hi> 2 <hi>Th.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>2. and partly becauſe of the uſual unſucceſsfulneſſe of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:124811:30"/> diſputes, eſpecially with men who cannot feel the ſtreſſe of an argument. But at length I reſolved to gratifie good peoples deſire, having given this ſolution to my own obj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctions; to the firſt, that though the men would not admit of any orderly diſpute, yet ſomwhat might in a more looſe diſcourſe be ſpok<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, which might be an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidote to preſerve from the malignity of their venom caſt abroad at a venture, and ſo the devil might be beat at his own weap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, and out-ſhot in his own bow, and a leſſe rational way of argu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng might God uſe for good, as the Devil did fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hurt. And I did hope that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f I did thus <hi>anſwer a fool <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cco ding to his folly,</hi> I ſhould eſcape the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of <hi>being alſo like him, P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ov</hi> 26.4. To the ſecond Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction I replied, that want of ſucceſſe was no more cogent an argum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt againſt diſputing than preaching; and I added, that God had not left diſputes without witneſſe of his approb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion (if that muſt needs be meaſured by the event) <hi>Acts</hi> 6.9, 10. <hi>Then there aroſe certain of the Synagogue, which is call<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d the Synagogue of the Libertines,</hi> &amp;c, <hi>dispu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing with Stephen, and they were not able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the wiſdom and spirit by which he ſpake.</hi> And ſeeing the Quakers were <hi>Libertines</hi> (or worſe) though I was not <hi>Stephen</hi> for like meaſure of wiſdom and ſpirit, I need not altogether deſpair of his ſucceſſe. And beſides theſe, other conſiderations offer'd their ſervice, <hi>viz.</hi> that they are a people who triumph and brag when we decline diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, forgetting the wiſe caution of King <hi>Ahab,</hi> a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourer of their way (I mean enmity againſt the true Prophets) Let not him that girdeth on his harneſſe, boaſt himſelf as he that putteth it off, 1 <hi>King<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 20.21. And many ſimple people are apt to ſuſpect our Call and Doctrine, when we ſeem unwilling openly to m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ntain them againſt oppoſers. And me thought that Scripture (which came to mind) did import a liberty, if not a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. <hi>Anſwer a fool according to his folly, leſt he be wiſe in
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:124811:30"/> his own conceit, Prov.</hi> 26.5 And I mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t confeſſe that the example of ſo R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>verend and Lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d a perſon, as Mr. <hi>Richard Baxte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> who yi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lded to a v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>courſe with an unreaſonable railing fell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w, wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>thout its influ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e upon me, betwe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n whom and the Quakers, I was to deal with (though i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>norant and un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rned men) the inequality is very inconſiderable, in c mpariſon or what it is between him and them. But eſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cially the rea <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns which he gives of printing againſt them, in his <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to the <hi>Quak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs Cat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m,</hi> as al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o aga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſt other like wr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tches, in the Preface to the <hi>Defence of t e Wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>terſhire Petition,</hi> did maſter my underſtanding, and he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d to fix my wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering thoughts, in a reſolution to diſcourſe with them. When I came among them, they aſſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed that there is a <hi>Light in every man, which is Christ;</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t <hi>in this life men may be perfect, and free from ſin,</hi> that <hi>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tified not by Christ without, but wi hin them.</hi> Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y al o urg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral trivial arguments againſt our <hi>Miniſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y,</hi> as, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g hire, being call'd Maſters, wearing lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> robes, add<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng meanings to the Scripture.</hi> To eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch aſſertions I ſaid ſomwhat, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eplied to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a guments againſt our Miniſtry (as their unmannerly clamour would give leave) for they would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndeavour to drown my vo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce by theirs, when I ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke anything that pinched them; and parti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly when I urged 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>ult.</hi> That look as Chriſt was made ſin for us, ſo were we made the righteouſneſſe of God in him, but the former was by im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>utation, not by inherence, Chriſt <hi>knowing no ſin</hi> (by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xperience of its working <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n himſelf) and therefore ſo th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> latter: I was interrupted by the two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>peakers, <hi>Luke Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rd,</hi> and <hi>Stephen Hubberdy,</hi> with ſuch rude langu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>thou lie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, thou l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt,</hi> and they did not once offer any other confutation, though I u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ged th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m to the attempt, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eld my tongue in exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctation, but in ſtead of a reply, lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ked upon one another like men aſtoniſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, and made ſo long <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pauſe
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:124811:31"/> that many of the hearers cried out, they are ſilenced, they have nothing to ſay. At length they recovered them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and talked on in a diſcourſe ſo impertinent and independent, that I began to admire the men, for order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their words ſo warily, as that they were all birds of a feather, and not one bird of another feather ſuch as reaſon and pertinency to be found in the whole flock. At the end of the day, the former of the two men above mentioned (being conſcious to himſelf how little he had done for his cauſe) made an open challenge of diſpute between me and other of their friends (meaning their fellow-Quakers) to whom I replied that I would not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point a time for diſcourſe with ſuch ignorant and railing men as himſelf and his companion, but if Mr. <hi>Fiſher</hi> would undertake it, I would enter the liſts with him. This Mr. <hi>Fiſher</hi> (leſt thou be ignorant Courteous Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the reaſon why I ſingled out him from the reſt) was ſometime a Miniſter, and well reputed of for his gifts in this County. And I had a little hope, that ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he had more reaſon than the reſt of that way, he would not let it lie dormant, but awaken it into exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, and make ſome uſe of it. And according to my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the chalenger promiſed to procure Mr. <hi>Fiſher</hi> to come and debate their Tenents that day moneth, being the 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>April,</hi> 1659. (a time which he pitched, becauſe his friends occaſions (as he pretended) would not admit them to come ſooner. The day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come,<note place="margin">Witneſses, Mr. Oldfield, Mr. Foxton, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> Mr. <hi>Fiſher</hi> appeared at <hi>Peters</hi> Church in our Town, but pretended that he knew not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Lord would open or ſhut his mouth, and therefore declined any diſcourſe; and I was fain to wait his leiſure, and to talk with one <hi>Richard Hubberthorn,</hi> who needed a bridle as much as the other
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:124811:31"/> did a ſpur, and made good the Proverb, whoſo bold as blind Bayard? A right Quaker, whoſe diſcourſe want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all the ingredients that ſhould have made it ſavoury, <hi>viz.</hi> truth, ſenſe, and pertinence. And when he was ſilenced, came in for a reſerve one <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orge Whitehead,</hi> a man that ſeemed to have more mother wit, than the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but as little of the Spirit of God (unleſſe that be a Spirit of errour and contradiction, and then I judge he had a plentiful meaſure.) At length Mr. <hi>Fiſher</hi> came in to help him at a dead lift, and with him I diſcourſed till night. And though they had made themſelves naked to their ſhame, eſpecially by the Doctrines of perfection and juſtification by works, yet to ſet a good face on the matter, they urged for another diſpute, which I granted them the next day at the School houſe. And the Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day following, <hi>April</hi> 16. I received a challenge from <hi>Hubberthorn</hi> (who looked upon himſelf as contemned the other two dayes, becauſe the people after they had heard him a while, cried out to him to hold his tongue, or ſpeak to the purpoſe) to defend my own Call to the Miniſtry, and hear the proof of his, which I would not anſwer, but upon condition, that Mr. <hi>Fiſher</hi> would alſo debate thoſe two queſtions, <hi>Whether the Scriptures he the Word of God?</hi> and <hi>whether the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt God-man be ſatisfactory to the Juſtice of God for the ſin of man?</hi> Which I confeſſe I deſired the people might hear their judgement in, that they might ſee them in their co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, and not miſtake them for better men than they are. And accordingly we agreed to m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et at the School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe the Tueſday following <hi>April</hi> 19. I preſume thou art now liſtning to hear the iſſue, and I will tell thee truly what it was, that many bleſſed God for the caution they received againſt their Principles, which now they underſtood plainly (though not without much ado, did
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:124811:32"/> I get them to ſpeak, as that every one might know their meaning.) And ſome good people who formerly had a favourable opinion of them, and thought that they and we differ'd but in terms, in the Doct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ne of Juſtification, and the Scripture<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> being the Word of God, do now loath a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reſt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m, as men that <hi>preach another Gospel, which y is not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nother, and would p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>vert the Goſpel of Chriſt, Ga.</hi> 1 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 7 8. And the truth is, we have <hi>reum confitentem,</hi> the Malefactors own Confeſſion, for Mr. <hi>Fiſher</hi> did op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nly declare to the people,<note place="margin">Mr. S yli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rd, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> D <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>le, Mr. Fox on Jur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſt day of our diſpute, that the Goſpel which I preached, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uld never br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m to H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aven plainly enough intimating ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>by, that he preached another Go pel. And 'tis a paſſage not to be omitted, that as often as Mr. <hi>Fiſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> had occaſion to menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me of our Lord Chriſt,<note place="margin">Mr S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d. Mr. A <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>y Oldfield. Mr. Fox<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on.</note> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld call him <hi>The man Chriſt Jeſus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hom you call</hi> (ſpeaking to me) <hi>God-man;</hi> and being o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ten a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ked whether he did not call him lo too, I could never g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t an anſwer, and truly hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nce may well be interpreted conſent to the horrid A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ian Blaſphemy. 'Tis al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o obſervable that Mr. <hi>Fiſher</hi> would not diſcourſe the point of Chriſts ſatisfaction,<note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Seyli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rd, Mr. Rumſey.</note> but put me off w th general terms, that all that Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt did was pleaſing to God, and ſo ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te down, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ave way to his comp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nion. And we h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt ground to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>liev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that he denies it, for many o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them do (as we find <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ny of their printed Papers) and they p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>etend to have no d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fferences in opinion among themſelves. And thou c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſt not be ignorant that the denial of it in conjunction with their juſtification by
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:124811:32"/> works, does not only lop the branches, but grub up by the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry roots the Goſpel, which thou haſt received. I cannot omit another remarkeable paſſage, and 'tis this, that in the midſt of our diſcourſe, <hi>April</hi> 13. one of the Quakers (whoſe name I cannot learn) cried out for audience,<note place="margin">Mr. Domſel, Mr. Tho Foxton, Mr. Tho. Rumſey.</note> pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he had ſomwhat to ſay <hi>from the Lord,</hi> and varying h s phraſe, <hi>In the Name of the Lord,</hi> but he was denied liberty, becauſe he was none of the Diſputants, but the man was ſo o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtreperous, that upon promiſe of ſpeaking br efly, we were glad for quietneſſe ſake to hear him. But what wouldſt thou think was his meſſage from the Lord? It was to accuſe a godly Miniſter there pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, of ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndering <hi>Samuel Fiſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mr. Peter Dom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell,</note> by affi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ming that the ſaid <hi>S. Fiſher</hi> had been at <hi>Rome,</hi> and received <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Penſion from the Pope, and the accuſer pretended to have a witneſſe ready to prove it. The Miniſter ſtood up at the accuſation, and demanded when and where he ſpake theſe words? It was anſwered, the laſt night (meaning <hi>April</hi> 12.) between <hi>Sandwich</hi> and <hi>Staple</hi> (a Countrey <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ariſh about 4 miles diſtant.) To the anſwer, the Miniſter replied, that he was at that time in <hi>Sandwich,</hi> and was not out of Town that night. And (to ſave further trouble ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and proving) the Quakers witneſſe of his own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord cried out that it was not th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Miniſter accuſed,<note place="margin">Mr. Rob. Wilkinſon.</note> but the Miniſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Staple,</hi> that ſpake the words a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the time and place mentioned. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſuppoſe good Reader, thou wilt be ready to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xcuſe the accuſer, and to ſay, it was but a miſtake of one man for another, and truly I ſhould joyn with thee, if the man were of any other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:124811:33"/> then Quakeriſm, for theſe men pretend to be immediately ſent by God about trivial things, which if they really were, they could no more miſtake in the perſons to whom, than the meſſage whereabout they are ſent. And ſurely had God ſent this Quaker to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince a man of ſlander, he would have ſent him to the right man. And I think we may well conclude them as ſar from infallibility in Doctrine, as in matters of fact. And 'tis worthy thy conſideration, that when the accuſer had nothing to ſay for himſelf,<note place="margin">Mr. Foxton, Mr. Oldfield, Mr. Rum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey, Jurates.</note> but ſlunk down among his fellow Quakers, M. <hi>Fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> holp him with a Lie, and told us that the man did not ſay <hi>from the Lord,</hi> or <hi>in the Name of the Lord,</hi> but <hi>in the fear of the Lord,</hi> which the man hearing, pluck'd up his Spirits, and ſtood up again, boldly affirming the latter words to be his. When as he had no ſuch plea for himſelf, till it was put into his mouth; and the generality of the people did then hout at Mr. <hi>Fiſher,</hi> for a lyar, and did then and do ſtill af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm that the man ſpake the former words. And as for the matter whereof Mr. <hi>Fiſher</hi> was accuſed, part of it he denied not, namely, that he had been at <hi>Rome,</hi> but that he received a Penſion from the Pope, he utterly denied, which yet that is probably as true, for I have it from ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good hands, that in his late travel to <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> and thence to <hi>Rome,</hi> he had as good Bills of exchange, as moſt Gentlemen that travel, and yet 'tis well known that he hath no viſible eſtate. And the Quakers who came to hear the diſpute (who I ſuppoſe would not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly him) did report, that he did bear his witneſſe againſt the Pope and Cardinals at <hi>Rome,</hi> and yet they ſuffered him not to be meddled with, which how unprobable it is, let all men judge, but how much more probable, that
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:124811:33"/> the true cauſe of his ſafety was his compliance with them, the Doctrines which he broaches among us, and (as he ſaies) in all other places, being theirs, and a fair inlet to their Bag and Baggage. And to aſſure the Reader of the likelihood of his compliance with the Antichriſtian Faction, thou maiſt pleaſe to know, that the 12. inſtant (<hi>Engliſh</hi> account) two honeſt, and credible men of <hi>Sandwich</hi> had ſome diſcourſe with Mr. <hi>Fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> at <hi>Dunkirk,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mr. Tho. Foxton Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, Tho. Barber, Cooper.</note> and he told them that he looked upon the Jeſuits and Friars there, to be ſounder in Doctrine than thoſe we call the Reformed Churches. This they are ready to teſtifie at any time upon call.</p>
            <p>Another paſſage I have to acquaint thee with, <hi>viz.</hi> that the aforeſaid Mr. <hi>Fiſher,</hi> in conference with the above-na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Sandwich</hi> men at <hi>Dunkirk,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mr. Tho. Foxton, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, Tho. Barber, Cooper.</note> 
               <hi>May</hi> 12. <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſtile, did affirm that he himſelf is above Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and that there is no more uſe of them in this life, to many perſons, than there is of a Candle-light, when the ſun ſhines, and he gave inſtance in the uſeleſneſſe of Baptiſm, and the Lords Supper.</p>
            <p>And the ſame witneſſes were credibly informed at <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kirk,</hi> that Mr. <hi>Fiſher</hi> hath great Bills of Exchange from a Quaking <hi>London</hi> Merchant, and may take up four hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pound if he will.</p>
            <p>And hundreds of people can teſtifie how light he made of the charge of Popery, on the firſt day of the Diſpute,<note place="margin">John Boys <hi>Eſq;</hi> Mr. Ch. Nichols, Mr. Th. Foxton, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> when I pluck'd <hi>Ameſius</hi> 4 <hi>Tome</hi> againſt <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> and offer'd to read part of it out of the Latine into Engliſh; and with
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:124811:34"/> a geſture of deriſion he replyed, that <hi>Bellarmine</hi> held ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Truths which muſt not be rejected becauſe he held them, and he gave for inſtance that Chriſt was the Son of God. And as for the ſtate of the Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtions, two of them, <hi>viz. The light of Nature,</hi> and <hi>Perfection,</hi> I need not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce any witneſſes to prove, becauſe they conſtantly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m them, but as for the reſt, they are wont to juggle &amp; equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate about them.<note place="margin">Henry Oxenden, John Boys, <hi>Eſq;</hi> M. Nath. Barry, Mr. Tho Seyli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, Mr. Ch. Nichols, Miniſters.</note> The terms of the third Queſtion were, <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good works be the meritorious cauſe of our Juſtification?</hi> which was expreſly affirmed by them.</p>
            <p>And this being ſo groſſe and Popiſh, <hi>Luke Howard</hi> one of the Quakers preſent at the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute,<note place="margin">Mr. Nath. Barry.</note> hath ſince denied that they did ſo affirm. And in the Fourth queſtion Mr. <hi>Fiſher</hi> denied that <hi>the Books commonly called the Old and N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w Testament were appointed of God for a ſtanding Rule of Faith and Life.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Henry Oxenden, Eſq; M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Tho. Seyliard, Mr. Ch. Nichols, Min. Mr. Antho. Oldfield, Mr. Tho. Foxton, Mr. Tho. Rumſey. Jurates.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And for the laſt, the infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of their Miniſtry the three Jurates of <hi>Sandwich</hi> in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, will teſtifie that they did af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm their Miniſtry to be infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <p>To conclude all, I ſhall give thee a taſt of the craft even of the female Sex, in evading Scriptures. One of them was challenged for breaking the rule, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.34. <hi>Let your women keep ſilence in the Church, for it is not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem to speak,</hi> &amp;c. To which challenge ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, that is ſpoken of the women that have husbands at home to learn of, <hi>v.</hi> 38. but I have none, but am a maid.</p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:124811:34"/>
            <p>Another (who was a wife) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alſo challenged for preaching publickly,<note place="margin">Mr. Tho. Foxton.</note> and that Scripture ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged againſt her, <hi>I ſuffer not a woman to teach, nor to u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurp authority ov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r the man,</hi> &amp;c. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.12. She rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily replied, that was ſpoken of the woman who was in the tranſgreſſion, but I am not one of them, (meaning it ſeems that women who are perfect, had the liberty of teaching, which was denied to other women.) And I had ſome private diſcourſe with a Gentlewoman a Quaker,<note place="margin">Mrs. Dor. Gudder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</note> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging her with that Scriptur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rk</hi> 7.13. <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>king the Word of God of none eff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct,</hi> which is ſpoken of the fifth Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>v</hi> 9, 12. (part of the wri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ten Word) to prove that the Scripture cals it ſelf by the name of <hi>the Word of God;</hi> and perceiving her at a loſſe, I p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſ'd her for an anſwer, in ſtead whereof ſhe put me a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion,<note place="margin">Mrs. Mary Paramour.</note> wouldſt thou not have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e imitate the man Chriſt in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll things? To which when I anſwered, yes, in ſuch things as are intended for our imitation, ſhe replies, the man Chriſt did not alwaies anſwer ſuch cavilling queſtions as were asked him, neither will I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſwer thee. And when ſhe was urged with thoſe Scriptu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16 and other Epiſtles, which enjoyn Saluta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ions, ſhe pretended that ſhe not being a <hi>Roman,</hi> nor <hi>Corinthian,</hi> what <hi>Paul</hi> wrote to them, was nothing to her, unleſſe the Spirit within her did prompt her to do the ſame things. And that thou maiſt ſee how great a ſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe they lay upon ſmall matters, I will tell thee a true ſtory (which perhaps may move thy laugh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er) that a Kinſman by marriage of the ſame Gentlewomans making offer to ſalute her at his own houſe, <hi>April</hi> 12, 1659.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:124811:35"/> ſhe went two or three ſteps back with theſe words, <hi>I have renounced the Devil and the Fleſh long ſince, prethee forbear that custom of the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things I thought good to add (at the deſire of ſome worthy perſons) which elſe I had omitted, that the world may take notice not onely of the wickedneſſe, but of the abſurdity of theſe peoples Principles.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:124811:35"/>
            <head>BOOKS ſold by <hi>John Allen</hi> at the Riſing SUNNE in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Caryl</hi>'s
<list>
                  <item>5th. Vol.</item>
                  <item>7th. Vol.</item>
                  <item>8th. Vol.</item>
                  <item>9th Vol.</item>
               </list> on <hi>Job.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Beza Novum Teſtamentum.</hi> Fol.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Allens</hi> Scripture Chronologie. 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> Call to the unconverted. 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Lukins</hi> practice of Godlineſſe. 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>A Catechiſm of the chief Heads of Chriſtian Religion, by Mr. <hi>Davenport</hi> &amp; Mr. <hi>Hooke</hi> of <hi>New-England.</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Faith and Order owned and practiſed in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregational Churches in <hi>England,</hi> agreed upon and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented unto by their Elders &amp; meſſengers at their meeting at the <hi>Savoy, Octob.</hi> 12, 1658.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Cottons</hi> Treatiſe on the Covenant of Grace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Johannes Becoldus Redivivus,</hi> the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Quaker, the <hi>German Enthuſiaſt</hi> revived.</p>
            <p>A Defence and Juſtification of Miniſters Maintenance by Tythes, and of Infant-Baptiſm, Humane Learning, and the Sword of the Magiſtrate, which ſome Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts falſly call four ſandy Pillars, and Popiſh Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb facs="tcp:124811:36"/> of our Miniſtry and Churches; written by <hi>Immanuel Bourne</hi> Paſtor to the Congregation at <hi>Waltham</hi> in the County of <hi>Leiceſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bytery and Independency vindicated in anſwer to Mr. <hi>John Tympſons</hi> Treatiſe of a free admiſſion to the Lords T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ble. Its now in the Preſs.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Gatt ker</hi> againſt judi ial Aſtrology.</p>
            <p>The vanity of judicial A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rology, written by <hi>Gaſſandus</hi> Mathemetical Prof<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſor to the Ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Several Caſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Conſcience concerning <hi>ASTROLO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GY,</hi> and ſeekers unto Aſtrologers anſwered, bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h from the VVord of God, and from the Teſtimony of our moſt godly and eminent Divines; publiſhed by a Friend to the Truth, in which Book Judicial Aſtrologie is proved to be</p>
            <p n="1">1. Expreſly fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bidden by the VVord of God as a grand offence, and ought not to be practiſed, counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanced, nor tollerated, <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u.</hi> 18.10, 11. <hi>Lev.</hi> 20.6. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 47.13, 14. <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.2.</p>
            <p>The Reaſons why it is ſo expreſly forbidden, are:</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is a practice whereby men do aſſume to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves that which is peculiar unto God, <hi>viz.</hi> Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment concerning future events either concerning King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms or Perſons, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 41.22, 23.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe it draws the hearts of men from God the Father, and Chriſt his Son, from conſidering the VVorks of the one, &amp; hearking to the words of the other, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 5.12. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.8, 18, 19. <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.10, 16.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Becauſe it is falſe, deluſive, and uncertain, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 44.15.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Becauſe it nouriſheth vain and forbidden hopes and fears, <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.2.</p>
            <p>All which Conſiderations publiſhed are to this end.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As an alarum, that the Conſciences of thoſe that ſtudy it may be awakened, that they may be fully convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb facs="tcp:124811:36"/> of the great evill that is in it, that abhorring ſuch an abominable evil that is ſo hateful to God, and a reall trouble to the Conſciences of good men; by leaving the ſin, they may avoid the puniſhment.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That Conſcientious Magiſtrates may know how nearly it concerns them to do their duties, in vindicating the Glory of God, by putting a period to the ſtudy of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial Aſtrology, a practiſe indeed that brings the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God into ſo much contempt in the world.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Laſtly, That all thoſe that have a deſire to learn it, and thoſe who enquire of Aſtrologers what good or ill Fortune (as they term it) ſhall happen to them in the courſe of their lives may through Gods Grace ſtifle ſuch unlawful deſires; all which through the Grace of God ſhall be the prayers and ſupplications of him (put up in the name of the Lord Jeſus) who is their friend to his power,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>JOHN ALLEN.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>
                  <hi>He that converteth a ſinner from the errour of his way, ſhall ſave a ſoul from death, and ſhall hide a multitude of ſins,</hi> James <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.20.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
